指
环
王
Ⅱ
-你休想通过  -甘道夫
- You cannot pass! - Gandalf!
我是秘火的服侍者
I am a servant of the Secret Fire,
阿诺尔之焰的持有者
wielder of the flame of Anor.
退回到魔影世界去
Go back to the Shadow.
黑暗之火无法击倒我  邪淫的地狱之火
The dark fire will not avail you, flame of Udun!
休想越过我的阻挡
You shall not pass!
不  不
No! No!
甘道夫
Gandalf!
快跑  傻瓜
Fly, you fools.
不
No!
甘道夫
Gandalf!
怎么了  弗罗多先生
What is it, Mr. Frodo?
没什么
Nothing.
做了个梦
Just a dream.
双 塔 奇 兵  加长版
你看得见底吗
Can you see the bottom?
看不到  别往下看  山姆  继续爬
No! Don't look down, Sam! Just keep going!
接住  快抓住  弗罗多先生
Catch it! Grab it, Mr. Frodo!
弗罗多先生
Mr. Frodo!
我想我到底了
I think I've found the bottom.
沼泽  绳子  天晓得什么东西
Bogs and rope, and goodness knows what.
不正常  都不正常
It's not natural. None of it.
-里面是什么  -没什么
- What's in this? - Nothing.
就是些调料
Just a bit of seasoning.
我想也许哪天晚上
I thought maybe if we was
可以吃个烤鸡什么的
having a roast chicken one night or something.
烤鸡
Roast chicken?!
谁知道呢
You never know.
山姆  我亲爱的山姆
Sam. My dear Sam.
这个很特别  是全夏尔最好的盐
It's very special, that. It's the best salt in all the Shire.
是不一样
It is special.
家的感觉
It's a little bit of home.
这绳子不能留在这  会被人跟踪
We can't leave this here for someone to follow us down.
谁会跟下来  弗罗多先生
Who's gonna follow us down here, Mr. Frodo?
真可惜  这是加拉德瑞尔女王送我的
It's a shame, really. Lady Galadriel gave me that.
货真价实的精灵绳
Real Elvish rope.
现在也没办法
Well, there's nothing for it.
这可是我打的结
It's one of my knots.
不可能轻易解开
Won't come free in a hurry.
不愧是精灵绳啊
Real Elvish rope.
魔多
Mordor.
那是中洲世界
The one place in middle-earth
我们绝不想靠近的地方
we don't want to see any closer.
而如今我们偏要往那儿去
And it's the one place we're trying to get to.
一个无法到达的终点
It's just where we can't get.
面对现实吧  弗罗多先生  我们迷路了
Let's face it, Mr. Frodo, we're lost.
我觉得甘道夫不希望我们走这条路
I don't think Gandalf meant for us to come this way.
他不希望发生的事太多了  山姆
He didn't mean for a lot of things to happen, Sam...
可却都发生了
but they did.
弗罗多先生
Mr. Frodo?
是魔戒的关系吧
It's the Ring, isn't it?
它越来越沉了
It's getting heavier.
-我们还有什么吃的  -让我看看
- What food have we got left? - Let me see.
有了  真好
Oh, yes. Lovely.
有兰巴斯饼(行路面包)  瞧
Lembas bread. And look!
更多兰巴斯饼(行路面包)
More lembas bread.
我一般不喜欢外族的食物
I don't usually hold with foreign food...
但这种精灵饼还不赖
but this Elvish stuff, it's not bad.
什么都影响不了你  山姆
Nothing ever dampens your spirits, does it, Sam?
那些乌云除外
Those rain clouds might.
这里好眼熟
This looks strangely familiar.
因为我们来过这
It's because we've been here before.
我们在绕圈子
We're going in circles.
哪来的恶臭
What is that horrid stink?
这附近肯定有个臭气熏天的沼泽
I warrant there's a nasty bog nearby.
-你闻到了吗  -对
- Can you smell it? - Yes.
我闻到了
I can smell it.
这里还有别人
We're not alone.
小偷  小偷
The thieves. The thieves.
卑鄙的霍比特小偷
The filthy little thieves.
它在哪里
Where is it?
在哪里
他们从我们这偷走了
They stole it from us.
我的宝贝
My precious.
诅咒他们  我们恨他们
Curse them, we hates them!
它是我们的  我们的  我们要把它拿回来
It's ours, it is, and we wants it!
这是刺叮剑
This is Sting.
你之前见过吧  咕噜
You've seen it before... haven't you, Gollum?
放开他  不然我就割断你的喉咙
Release him or I'll cut your throat.
好热
It burns!
好热啊
It burns us!
冷死了
It freezes!
臭精灵的绳子
Nasty Elves twisted it.
-把它拿开  -你给我闭嘴
- Take it off us! - Quiet, you!
这样不行
It's hopeless.
魔多的奥克会听见这叫声
Every Orc in Mordor's going to hear this racket.
-把它绑在这里我们走吧  -不
- Let's just tie him up and leave him. - No!
那样我们会死的  会死的
That would kill us! Kill us!
那是你罪有应得
It's no more than you deserve!
也许他确实该死
Maybe he does deserve to die.
但我现在看着他  倒觉得他很可怜
But now that I see him, I do pity him.
只要别人待我们好  我们也会对他们好
We be nice to them if they be nice to us.
放开我们吧
Take it off us.
我们发誓为您效力
We swears to do what you wants.
我们发誓
We swears.
你发的誓我可不相信
There's no promise you can make that I can trust.
我们发誓
We swears...
会服侍宝贝的主人
to serve the master of the precious.
我们以...
We will swear on...
以宝贝之名起誓
on the precious.
咕噜  咕噜
Gollum. Gollum.
魔戒太狡猾
The Ring is treacherous.
它会刻意影响你的誓言
It will hold you to your word.
是的
Yes...
以宝贝之名
On the precious.
我不相信你
I don't believe you!
-下来  我叫你下来  -山姆
- Get down! I said, down! - Sam!
他这是骗我们
He's trying to trick us.
放了他  他会趁我们睡觉时掐死我们
If we let him go, he'll throttle us in our sleep.
-你认识去魔多的路吗  -认识
- You know the way to Mordor? - Yes.
你以前去过吗
You've been there before?
去过
Yes.
你带我们去魔栏农
You will lead us to the Black Gate.
去魔栏农  去魔栏农  去魔栏农
To the Gate, to the Gate! To the Gate,
主人说去魔栏农
the master says. Yes!
不  我们绝不回去  不去那  别听他的
No! We won't go back. Not there. Not to him.
他们不能逼我们  咕噜  咕噜
They can't make us. Gollum! Gollum!
但我们发过誓要效忠宝贝的主人
But we swore to serve the master of the precious.
不  那里到处是灰尘  还会很口渴
No. Ashes and dust and thirst there is,
坑坑洼洼的
and pits, pits, pits.
还有很多很多的奥克
And Orcses, thousands of Orcses.
邪眼永远盯着你
And always the Great Eye watching, watching.
回来  快回来
Hey! Come back now! Come back!
看  我告诉过你吧
There! What did I tell you?
他跑了  本性难移啊
He's run off, the old villain.
他的诺言不值钱
So much for his promises.
这边  霍比特人
This way, Hobbits.
跟着我
Follow me!
梅里
Merry!
你太慢了  我们的主人等急了
You're late. Our master grows impatient.
他现在就要夏尔的矮人
He wants the Shire-rats now.
我可不帮奥克蛆虫做事
I don't take orders from Orc-maggots.
萨茹曼会得到他的俘虏
Saruman will have his prize.
我们会亲自献上
We will deliver them.
梅里
Merry!
梅里  快醒醒
Merry? Wake up.
我朋友病了
My friend is sick.
他要喝水  求求你
He needs water. Please!
病了是吗  给他来点药  小子们
Sick, is he? Give him some medicine, boys!
住手
Stop it!
怎么喝不下去呀
Can't take his draught!
-别碰他  -为什么
- Leave him alone! - Why?
你想来点吗
You want some?
乖乖闭上你的嘴
Then keep your mouth shut.
梅里
Merry.
皮皮
Hello, Pip.
-你受伤了  -我没事
- You're hurt. - I'm fine.
-我在演戏  -演戏?
- It was just an act. - An act?
看  你也上当了
See? I fooled you too.
别担心我  皮平
Don't worry about me, Pippin.
怎么回事  你闻到了什么
What is it? What do you smell?
人类
Man-flesh.
他们跟上来了
They've picked up our trail.
阿拉贡
Aragorn.
快走
Let's move!
他们加快了步伐
Their pace has quickened.
准是闻到了我们的气味
They must have caught our scent.
快点
Hurry!
快点  吉姆利
Come on, Gimli!
整整跑了三天三夜
Three days and nights pursuit.
没吃东西没休息
No food. No rest.
周围除了石头还是石头  一点踪迹也没有
And no sign of our quarry, but what bare rock can tell.
罗瑞恩别针不会无缘无故掉下来
Not idly do the leaves of Lorien fall.
他们或许还活着
They may yet be alive.
还差不到一天的路程  快来
Less than a day ahead of us. Come.
快点  吉姆利  我们快赶上了
Come, Gimli! We're gaining on them!
长途跋涉我可不在行
I'm wasted on cross-country.
矮人是天生的短跑健将
We Dwarves are natural sprinters.
短距离赛跑可是相当有威胁
Very dangerous over short distances.
洛汗国
Rohan.
驭马者(洛希尔人)的领地
Home of the Horse-lords.
这里有什么不对劲
There's something strange at work here.
某种邪恶的力量促使他们健步如飞
Some evil gives speed to these creatures.
却与我们作对
Sets its will against us.
莱戈拉斯  你的精灵眼看到什么
Legolas! What do your Elf-eyes see?
乌鲁克往东北方向走了
The Uruks turn northeast.
他们要带霍比特人去艾森加德
They are taking the Hobbits to Isengard.
萨茹曼
Saruman.
世界正在剧变
The world is changing.
现在还有谁能阻挡
Who now has the strength to stand against
艾森加德和魔多的大军
the armies of Isengard and Mordor?
还有谁能对抗索隆和萨茹曼
To stand against the might of Sauron and Saruman...
以及双塔结盟的力量
and the union of the two towers?
只要我们联手  索隆魔君
Together, my lord Sauron...
就能一统中洲
we shall rule this Middle-earth.
旧世界会在烈焰中燃尽
The Old World will burn in the fires of industry.
森林将会消失
The forests will fall.
新的势力就要崛起
A new order will rise.
我们将用奥克的尖兵利器
We will drive the machine of war with the sword and the spear...
和铿锵铁拳来推动战争
and the iron fists of the Orc.
我要他们两周内全副武装  整装待发
I want them armed and ready to march within two weeks!
但是  大人  人数太多了
But, my lord, there are too many!
不可能都武装齐备  武器不够
They cannot all be armed in time, we don't have the means.
建个河坝  截住河流
Build a dam, block the stream,
火炉日夜开动
work the furnaces night and day.
可是没那么多燃料
We don't have enough fuel to feed the fires.
门口就是范贡森林
The Forest of Fangorn lies on our doorstep.
-烧了它  -遵命
- Burn it. - Yes.
我们会为你而战
We will fight for you.
发誓
Swear it.
我们愿为萨茹曼奋战至死
We will die for Saruman.
洛希尔人抢占了你们的土地
The Horse-Men took your lands.
赶走了你们的人民
They drove your people
害你们只能住在山上与岩石而伴
into the hills to scratch a living off rocks.
凶手
Murderers!
夺回他们偷走的土地
Take back the lands they stole from you.
烧光每个村庄
Burn every village!
我们必须铲除我们的敌人
We have only to remove those who oppose us.
就从洛汗国开始
It will begin in Rohan.
这些农夫跟你作对太久
Too long have these peasants stood against you.
但再也不会了
But no more.
伊奥泰因  伊奥泰因
Eothain! Eothain!
带上你妹妹  两个人走会快些
You take your sister. You'll go faster with just two.
爸爸说伊奥泰因不能骑加鲁夫
Papa says Eothain must not ride Garulf.
他还不够高
He is too big for him.
听我说  你必须骑去埃多拉斯报警
Listen to me. You must ride to Edoras and raise the alarm.
-听明白了吗  -明白  妈妈
- Do you understand me? - Yes, Mama.
我不想走  不想走  妈妈
I don't want to leave. I don't want to go, Mama.
弗蕾达  我会去找你
Freda, I will find you there.
快走
Quickly!
走吧  孩子
Go, child.
魔君大人
Rohan, my lord...
洛汗国即将毁灭
is ready to fall.
希奥杰德
Theodred.
快去找王子
Find the king's son!
魔多会付出代价
Mordor will pay for this.
这些奥克不是从魔多来的
These Orcs are not from Mordor.
伊奥梅尔大人  这里
My Lord Eomer, over here!
他还活着
He's alive.
希奥杰德
Theodred.
您的儿子伤得很重  王上
Your son is badly wounded, my lord.
他中了奥克的埋伏
He was ambushed by Orcs.
如果我们不捍卫自己的国家
If we don't defend our country,
就会被萨茹曼夺走
Saruman will take it by force.
说谎
That is a lie.
白袍巫师萨茹曼一直是我们的盟友
Saruman the White has ever been our friend and ally.
格里马
Grima.
奥克在我们的土地上横行
Orcs are roaming freely across our lands.
肆意妄为  滥杀无辜
Unchecked. Unchallenged. Killing at will.
他们带有萨茹曼的白掌印记
Orcs bearing the White Hand of Saruman.
你为什么还要再给国王凭添烦恼
Why do you lay these troubles on an already troubled mind?
难道你看不出来吗
Can you not see?
你叔叔受够了你的牢骚
Your uncle is wearied by your malcontent...
还有你的好战
your warmongering.
好战?
Warmongering?
萨茹曼买通你多久了
How long is it since Saruman bought you?
他许诺了什么  格里马
What was the promised price, Grima?
等人类灭亡
When all the Men are dead,
你就能分得财宝吗
you will take your share of the treasure?
你一直窥视我妹妹的美貌
Too long have you watched my sister.
总是悄悄跟着她
Too long have you haunted her steps.
你管得太多了  伊奥蒙德之子  伊奥梅尔
You see much, Eomer, son of Eomund.
太多了
Too much.
你将被逐出洛汗
You are banished forthwith from the kingdom of Rohan...
以及其所有领地  违则处死
and all its domains under pain of death.
你无权这么做
You have no authority here.
你的命令一文不值
Your orders mean nothing.
这不是我下的命令
This order does not come from me.
而是国王
It comes from the king.
他早上签了字
He signed it this morning.
保持呼吸是诀窍
Keep breathing. That's the key.
呼吸
Breathe.
他们跑得就像
They've run as if the very whips
有人在后面鞭笞他们一样
of their masters were behind them.
让我们休息一下
We're not going no further...
不然我们就不走了
until we've had a breather.
生火
Get a fire going!
梅里
Merry!
我想离开夏尔
I think we might have made a mistake
可能是个错误  皮平
leaving the Shire, Pippin.
这是什么声音
What's making that noise?
是树
It's the trees.
什么
What?
还记得雄鹿地边界的老林子吗
You remember the Old Forest, on the borders of Buckland?
人们常说水里有东西
Folk used to say there was something
能让树长高
in the water that made the trees grow tall...
让树活起来
and come alive.
活起来?
Alive?
树能互相低语
Trees that could whisper...
互相交谈
talk to each other...
甚至走动
even move.
我饿死了
I'm starving.
我们这三天
We ain't had nothing but maggoty bread
只吃了蛆虫面包
for three stinking days.
为什么我们不开开荤呢
Why can't we have some meat?!
他们怎么样
What about them?
很新鲜啊
They're fresh.
他们不是食物
They are not for eating.
吃条腿怎么样
What about their legs?
反正他们用不着
They don't need those.
-看起来很诱人  -滚回去  废物
- They look tasty. - Get back, scum!
囚犯要毫发无伤地献给萨茹曼
The prisoners go to Saruman. Alive and unspoiled.
毫发无伤?
Alive?
凭什么要留活口  他们有什么交情
Why alive? Do they give good sport?
他们有东西  是精灵武器
They have something. An Elvish weapon.
主人要用来打仗
The master wants it for the war.
他们以为魔戒在我们这
They think we have the Ring.
要是他们发现我们没有  我们就死定了
As soon as they find out we don't, we're dead.
就一口
Just a mouthful...
小小一口
a bit of the flank.
看来有肉吃了  小崽子们
Looks like meat's back on the menu, boys.
皮平
Pippin.
我们走
Let's go.
走啊
Go on.
喊救命啊
Call for help.
尖叫啊
Squeal.
现在没人救得了你们
No one's going to save you now.
皮平
Pippin!
红日升起
A red sun rises.
昨夜定有杀戮
Blood has been spilled this night.
洛汗国的骠骑
Riders of Rohan...
骠骑国可有消息
what news from the Mark?
一个精灵  一个人类和一个矮人
What business does an Elf, a Man and a Dwarf
来里德马克有何贵干
have in the Riddermark?
快说
Speak quickly!
亮出名号  骑兵统帅
Give me your name, horse-master,
然后我再告诉你我是谁
and I shall give you mine.
你要是再长高点  小矮子
I would cut off your head, Dwarf...
我就能砍掉你的脑袋
if it stood but a little higher from the ground.
不等你动手  我就剁了你
You would die before your stroke fell.
我是阿拉松之子  阿拉贡
I am Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
这是格罗因之子  吉姆利
This is Gimli, son of Gloin,
还有来自幽暗森林的精灵莱戈拉斯
and Legolas of the Woodland Realm.
我们是洛汗和驭马者希奥顿的朋友
We are friends of Rohan and of Theoden, your king.
希奥顿已经敌友不分了
Theoden no longer recognizes friend from foe.
甚至六亲不认
Not even his own kin.
萨茹曼蛊惑国王的心智
Saruman has poisoned the mind of the king...
占领了这片土地
and claimed lordship over these lands.
我们都誓死效忠洛汗国
My company are those loyal to Rohan.
因此遭到驱逐
And for that, we are banished.
那个白袍巫师诡计多端
The White Wizard is cunning.
听说他身披兜帽斗篷
He walks here and there, they say...
神出鬼没
as an old man hooded and cloaked.
他的间谍无处不在
And everywhere, his spies slip past our nets.
我们不是间谍
We are no spies.
我们穿过平原向西追踪一群乌鲁克
We track a party of Uruk-hai westward across the plain.
他们抓住了我们的两个朋友
They have taken two of our friends captive.
乌鲁克已经死了  我们昨晚歼灭了他们
The Uruks are destroyed. We slaughtered them during the night.
应该有两个霍比特人
But there were two Hobbits.
你看到了吗
Did you see two Hobbits with them?
他们身材矮小  就像孩子
They would be small. Only children to your eyes.
我们没留活口
We left none alive.
把尸体堆起来烧了
We piled the carcasses and burned them.
死了吗
Dead?
抱歉
I am sorry.
哈苏费尔  阿罗德
Hasufel! Arod!
希望这些马驹能带给你们好运
May these horses bear you to better fortune
而不是同它们的前主人一个下场
than their former masters.
后会有期
Farewell.
去找你们的朋友吧
Look for your friends.
但别抱希望
But do not trust to hope.
这片土地已被神所遗弃
It has forsaken these lands.
向北前进
We ride north!
这是他们的小腰带
It's one of their wee belts.
愿他们安息
Hiro hyn hîdh ab 'wanath.
我们辜负了他们
We failed them.
有个霍比特人躺在这
A Hobbit lay here.
还有一个在这
And the other.
他们在爬行
They crawled.
他们被绑住了手
Their hands were bound.
他们割断绳子
Their bonds were cut.
跑到了这里
They ran over here.
被人抓住了
They were followed.
脱下腰带
The belt!
快跑
Run!
他们的足迹离开了战场
Tracks lead away from the battle...
跑进了范贡森林
into Fangorn Forest.
范贡
Fangorn?
他们疯了吗  居然跑进那里
What madness drove them in there?
甩掉他了吗  我想是甩掉了
Did we lose him? I think we lost him.
我要把你们恶心的小内脏都挖出来
I'm going to rip out your filthy little innards!
快出来
Come here!
树  爬到树上
Trees. Climb a tree.
他不见了
He's gone.
梅里
Merry!
我要在你的肚子上开个洞
Let's put a maggot hole in your belly!
跑啊  梅里
Run, Merry!
小奥克
Little Orcs.
它在说话  梅里  树在说话
It's talking, Merry. The tree is talking.
树
Tree?
我可不是树
I am no tree!
我是恩特(树人)
I am an Ent.
百树的牧人
A tree-herder.
森林的守护者
A shepherd of the forest.
别和它说话  梅里
Don't talk to it, Merry.
别鼓励它说话
Don't encourage it!
有些人叫我树须
Treebeard, some call me.
那你站在哪一边
And whose side are you on?
哪一边
Side?
我哪边也不是
I am on nobody's side...
因为没人站在我这边  小奥克
because nobody's on my side, little Orc.
没有人关心树木
Nobody cares for the woods anymore.
我们不是奥克  我们是霍比特人
We're not Orcs! We're Hobbits!
霍比特人
Hobbits?
从来没有听说过
Never heard of a Hobbit before.
听起来像是奥克的把戏
Sounds like Orc mischief to me!
他们拿着火把
They come with fire.
带着斧子
They come with axes.
又啃又咬  又砍又烧  横冲乱撞
Gnawing, biting, breaking, hacking, burning!
-破坏者  篡夺者  诅咒他们  -不
- Destroyers and usurpers! Curse them! - No!
你没明白  我们是霍比特人
You don't understand. We're Hobbits!
半身人
Halflings!
夏尔人
Shire-folk!
你们也许是
Maybe you are...
也许不是
and maybe you aren't.
白袍巫师自有答案
The White Wizard will know.
白袍巫师
The White Wizard?
萨茹曼
Saruman.
看见没  看见没
See? See?
我们带你们出来了
We've led you out.
快走  霍比特人  快走
Hurry, Hobbitses. Hurry!
幸好我们找到了你们
Very lucky we find you.
好霍比特人
Nice Hobbit.
沼泽  他领我们走进沼泽
It's a bog. He's led us into a swamp.
沼泽  没错  没错
A swamp, yes, yes.
主人  来吧
Come, master.
我们会带你们安全穿过迷雾
We will take you on safe paths through the mist.
来  霍比特人  来啊  我们快走
Come, Hobbits! Come! We go quickly.
我发现的  是我发现的
I found it. I did.
穿过沼泽的路
The way through the marshes.
奥克不会走  奥克不知道
Orcs don't use it. Orcs don't know it.
他们都绕很远的路
They go around for miles and miles.
快跟上
Come quickly.
我们要像影子一样无声无息
Soft and quick as shadows we must be.
我讨厌这地方  太安静了
I hate this place. It's too quiet.
这两天连鸟的影子都没有
There's been no sight nor sound of a bird for two days.
没有鸟饵可以吃
No, no birdseed to eat.
没有脆脆的鸟饵吃
No crunchable birdseed.
我们饿死了
We are famished! Yes!
饿死我们了  宝贝
Famished we are, precious!
给
Here.
什么味的
What does it eats?
好吃吗
Is it tasty?
快噎死我们了
It tries to chokes us!
我们不能吃霍比特人的食物
We can't eats Hobbit food!
我们会饿死的
We must starve!
那就饿死吧  正好摆脱你
Well, starve, then. And good riddance!
残忍的霍比特人
Oh, cruel Hobbit.
根本不在乎我们饿不饿
It does not care if we be hungry.
也不在乎我们的生死
Does not care if we should die.
不像主人
Not like master.
主人关心我们
Master cares.
主人了解我们
Master knows.
是啊
Yes.
宝贝
Precious.
一旦控制了我们
Once it takes hold of us...
就再也放不了手
it never lets go.
别碰我
Don't touch me!
都是死东西
There are dead things!
水里有死人脸
Dead faces in the water.
都死了  烂掉了
All dead. All rotten.
精灵  人类  奥克都一样
Elves and Men and Orcses.
很久以前这里有过一场大战
A great battle long ago.
死亡沼泽
Dead Marshes.
是的  是的  就是这个名字
Yes. Yes, that is their name.
走这边
This way.
别跟着鬼火
Don't follow the lights.
小心点
Careful now!
不然霍比特人会跌下去加入它们
Or Hobbits go down to join the dead ones...
变成小小的鬼火
and light little candles of their own.
弗罗多
Frodo!
-咕噜  -别跟着鬼火
- Gollum? - Don't follow the lights.
-咕噜  -弗罗多先生
- Gollum! - Mr. Frodo!
你没事吧
Are you all right?
好亮啊
So bright.
好美啊
So beautiful.
我们的宝贝
Our precious.
你说什么
What did you say?
主人该休息了
Master should be resting.
主人要保持体力
Master needs to keep up his strength.
-你是谁  -别问我们  不关你事
- Who are you? - Mustn't ask us. Not its business.
咕噜  咕噜
Gollum. Gollum.
甘道夫说你以前是河族人
Gandalf told me you were one of the river-folk.
心凉  手冰  刺骨寒
Cold be heart and hand and bone
离乡背井不简单
Cold be travelers far from home
他说你的人生很悲惨
He said your life was a sad story.
当日月陨落
They do not see what lies ahead,
前路迷朦无光
when sun has failed and moon is dead.
你以前和霍比特人差不多
You were not so very different from a Hobbit once.
对不对
Were you?
斯密戈
Smeagol.
你叫我什么
What did you call me?
那是你以前的名字  是吗
That was your name once, wasn't it?
很久之前
A long time ago.
我的名字
My name.
斯密戈
Smeagol.
黑骑手
Black Riders!
躲起来  躲起来
Hide! Hide!
快点  弗罗多  过来
Come on, Frodo. Come on!
快  他们要发现我们了  发现我们了
Quick! They will see us! They will see us!
-他们不是死了吗  -死了
- I thought they were dead. - Dead?
不  你杀不死他们  杀不死
No, you cannot kill them. No.
戒灵
Wraiths!
驾着飞骑的戒灵
Wraiths on wings!
他们在召唤它
They are calling for it.
召唤宝贝
They are calling for the precious.
弗罗多先生  没事的
Mr. Frodo! It's all right.
我在这
I'm here.
快点  霍比特人
Hurry, Hobbits.
魔栏农就快到了
The Black Gate is very close.
奥克的血
Orc blood.
这些足迹很奇怪
These are strange tracks.
这里的空气好厚
The air is so close in here.
这片森林很古老
This forest is old.
非常老
Very old.
充满回忆
Full of memory...
和愤怒
and anger.
树在互相交谈
The trees are speaking to each other.
吉姆利
Gimli!
放下你的斧子
Lower your ax.
他们感觉得到  朋友
They have feelings, my friend.
是精灵教的
The Elves began it.
唤醒树木  教他们说话
Waking up the trees, teaching them to speak.
会说话的树
Talking trees.
树有什么话好说的
What do trees have to talk about?
除了不断掉下来的松鼠粪便
Except the consistency of squirrel droppings.
阿拉贡  有动静
Aragorn, nad no ennas!
你听到了什么
Man cenich?
白袍巫师来了
The White Wizard approaches.
封住他的口
Do not let him speak.
别让他念咒
He will put a spell on us.
动作要快
We must be quick.
你们在追踪两个小霍比特人的足迹
You are tracking the footsteps of two young Hobbits.
他们在哪里
Where are they?
前天他们经过这里
They passed this way the day before yesterday.
遇见了意想不到之人
They met someone they did not expect.
满意了吗
Does that comfort you?
你是谁
Who are you?
快现身
Show yourself!
这不可能
It cannot be.
原谅我
Forgive me.
我以为你是萨茹曼
I mistook you for Saruman.
我是萨茹曼
I am Saruman.
或者说  是萨茹曼应该成为的样子
Or rather, Saruman as he should have been.
你掉下去了
You fell.
我穿过烈火
Through fire...
落入深水
and water.
从最深的地牢到最高的山峰
From the lowest dungeon to the highest peak...
我和魔苟斯的炎魔殊死搏斗
I fought with the Balrog of Morgoth.
最后我致命一击
Until at last I threw down my enemy...
把敌人的尸体扔下山峰
and smote his ruin upon the mountainside.
黑暗吞没了我
Darkness took me...
我失去了意识
and I strayed out of thought and time.
斗转星移
Stars wheeled overhead...
每天都像一辈子那么漫长
and every day was as long as a life age of the Earth.
但这并不是结束
But it was not the end.
我又重获新生
I felt life in me again.
被送了回来
I've been sent back...
完成我的使命
until my task is done.
甘道夫
Gandalf.
Gandalf?
是啊
Yes.
他们以前是这么叫我
That was what they used to call me.
灰袍甘道夫
Gandalf the Grey.
这是我以前的名字
That was my name.
甘道夫
Gandalf.
现在我是白袍甘道夫
I am Gandalf the White.
现在我回来
And I come back to you now...
助你们度过难关
at the turn of the tide.
这一旅程已经告一段落
One stage of your journey is over.
新的旅程又开始了
Another begins.
-我们必须全速赶往埃多拉斯  -埃多拉斯
- We must travel to Edoras with all speed. - Edoras?
这路程可不短啊
That is no short distance!
听说洛汗国有麻烦  国王病了
We hear of trouble in Rohan. It goes ill with the king.
是啊  还不容易治愈
Yes, and it will not be easily cured.
我们大老远跑来无功而返吗
Then we have run all this way for nothing?
我们要把可怜的霍比特人留在...
Are we to leave those poor Hobbits here...
这个阴森可怕的森林里吗
in this horrid, dark, dank tree-infested...?
我是说  迷人的
I mean, charming...
相当迷人的森林
quite charming forest.
梅里和皮平
It was more than mere chance
来到范贡森林并非偶然
that brought Merry and Pippin to Fangorn.
此地有股强大的力量沉睡已久
A great power has been sleeping here for many long years.
梅里和皮平的到来
The coming of Merry and Pippin
好比小石子的掉落
will be like the falling of small stones...
引起了山崩
that starts an avalanche in the mountains.
你这点一点都没变  亲爱的朋友
In one thing you have not changed, dear friend.
还是爱说谜语
You still speak in riddles.
自远古以来
A thing is about to happen
一件从未发生过的事就要发生了
that has not happened since the Elder Days.
恩特(树人)要苏醒了
The Ents are going to wake up...
-迸发他们强大的力量  -强大的力量
- and find that they are strong. - Strong?!
太好了
Oh, that's good.
那就别抱怨了  矮人
So stop your fretting, Master Dwarf.
梅里和皮平很安全
Merry and Pippin are quite safe.
其实他们远比你安全得多
In fact, they are far safer than you are about to be.
现在甘道夫的脾气比以前更怪了
This new Gandalf's more grumpy than the old one.
这是美亚拉斯的神驹
That is one of the Mearas...
除非我的眼睛被咒语蒙蔽看错了
unless my eyes are cheated by some spell.
这是捷影
Shadowfax.
它是众马之王
He is the lord of all horses...
伴随我走过重重困境
and has been my friend through many dangers.
我的花楸树
O rowan mine
你的光彩绚烂夺目
I saw you shine
夏日之下
Upon a summer's day
你的树冠一片金红
Upon your head how golden-red
如同高大的王冠
The crown you bore aloft
多美的诗啊
Such a beautiful verse.
-还很远吗  -不要急
- Is it much further? - Bru-ra-hroom. Don't be hasty.
也许你会觉得远
You might call it far, perhaps.
我的家在森林深处
My home lies deep in the forest...
就在那山脚下
near the roots of the mountain.
我答应甘道夫会保护你们的安全
I told Gandalf I would keep you safe.
有我保护  你们就很安全
And safe is where I'll keep you.
我相信你们也会喜欢下一首诗
I believe you will enjoy this next one too.
这也是我自己的创作
It's one of my own compositions.
开始
Right.
沉睡的树叶交织成顶
Beneath the roof of sleeping leaves
树木的美梦逐渐展开
And the dreams of trees unfold
当林地葱绿清凉
When woodland halls are green and cool
西风吹拂之时
And the wind is in the West
归来我身边
Come back to me
赞颂我的土地永远芳华
And say my land is best
睡吧  小小夏尔人
Sleep, little Shirelings.
安静而祥和
Heed no nightly noise.
熟睡到天明
Sleep till morning light.
我在林子里还有点事
I have business in the forest.
我要召集很多数人  他们必须来
There are many to call. Many that must come.
魔影笼罩着范贡
The Shadow lies on Fangorn.
树木的末日即将临近
The withering of all woods is drawing near.
东方的黑影越来越浓  逐渐成形
The veiling shadow that glowers in the east takes shape.
索隆不会容忍敌对的存在
Sauron will suffer no rival.
邪眼在巴拉督尔塔顶盯着  未曾停歇
From the summit of Barad-dur, his Eye watches ceaselessly.
但他还没那么强大  一直惶惶不可终日
But he is not so mighty yet that he is above fear.
长久以来他疑心重重
Doubt ever gnaws at him.
他听到了风声
The rumor has reached him.
努门诺尔的后裔还活着
The heir of Numenor still lives.
索隆惧怕你  阿拉贡
Sauron fears you, Aragorn.
他担心你的身份
He fears what you may become.
所以他很快就会攻击人类
And so he'll strike hard and fast at the world of Men.
他会借助傀儡萨茹曼摧毁洛汗
He will use his puppet Saruman to destroy Rohan.
战争迫在眉睫
War is coming.
洛汗必须自卫
Rohan must defend itself,
那是我们的第一个挑战
and therein lies our first challenge...
现在洛汗岌岌可危
for Rohan is weak and ready to fall.
控制国王的思想
The king's mind is enslaved,
这是萨茹曼的老花招
it's an old device of Saruman's.
他对希奥顿王控制得很深
His hold over King Theoden is now very strong.
索隆和萨茹曼正在收紧圈套
Sauron and Saruman are tightening the noose.
但就算他们再狡诈
But for all their cunning...
我们还有一个优势
we have one advantage.
他们还没找到魔戒
The Ring remains hidden.
我们设法摧毁魔戒的计划
And that we should seek to destroy it...
他压根就没有想过
has not yet entered their darkest dreams.
敌人的武器正朝着魔多前进
And so the weapon of the enemy is moving towards Mordor...
霍比特人手持魔戒
in the hands of a Hobbit.
一天天逼近末日山的烈焰
Each day brings it closer to the fires of Mount Doom.
我们必须相信弗罗多
We must trust now in Frodo.
胜败关键在于他能否
Everything depends upon speed...
尽快完成这次机密探险
and the secrecy of his quest.
别后悔离开他的决定
Do not regret your decision to leave him.
弗罗多必须独行
Frodo must finish this task alone.
他不是只身一人
He's not alone.
山姆和他一起
Sam went with him.
是吗
Did he?
真的吗  那好
Did he, indeed? Good.
非常好
Yes, very good.
魔多的魔栏农
The Black Gate of Mordor.
救救我们吧
Oh, save us.
要是老爹看到我们这样
My old Gaffer would have a thing or two to say
肯定又要发表言论了
if he could see us now.
主人说带他去魔多
Master says to show him the way into Mordor.
好斯密戈照做了  主人就这样说的
So good Smeagol does, master says so.
的确
I did.
就是那里
That's it, then.
我们进不去
We can't get past that.
看
Look!
门
The gate.
打开了
It's opening!
有条路可以下去
I can see a way down.
山姆  不
Sam, no!
主人
Master!
我没让你和我一起去  山姆
I do not ask you to come with me, Sam.
我知道  弗罗多先生
I know, Mr. Frodo.
我想在那里就算精灵斗篷也没用
I doubt even these Elvish cloaks will hide us in there.
-走  -不
- Now! - No!
不  不  主人
No! No, master!
他们会抓住你  会抓住你的
They catch you! They catch you!
别把它给他
Don't take it to him.
他想要宝贝
He wants the precious.
他一直在找它
Always he is looking for it.
而宝贝也想回到他身边
And the precious is wanting to go back to him.
但我们一定不能让他得手
But we mustn't let him have it.
别  还有一条路
No! There's another way.
一条更隐秘  更黑暗的路
More secret. A dark way.
你怎么不早说
Why haven't you spoken of this before?
因为主人没问
Because master did not ask.
他肯定在打鬼主意
He's up to something.
你是说还有别的路可以进魔多
Are you saying there's another way into Mordor?
对  有条路
Yes. There's a path...
还有阶梯
and some stairs.
然后
And then...
有一条隧道
a tunnel.
他都带我们到这了  山姆
He's led us this far, Sam.
弗罗多先生  不要
Mr. Frodo, no.
他一直遵守了诺言
He's been true to his word.
不要
No.
带路  斯密戈
Lead the way, Smeagol.
好斯密戈乐意帮忙
Good Smeagol always helps.
有人吗
Hello?
树须
Treebeard?
他去哪了
Where has he gone?
我昨晚做了个美梦
I had the loveliest dream last night.
一个装满了烟草的大桶
There was this large barrel, full of pipe-weed.
全被我们抽光了  然后
And we smoked all of it. And then...
你病了
you were sick.
要是再能抽一口老托比  我愿不惜一切
I'd give anything for a whiff of Old Toby.
你听到了吗
Did you hear that?
就是这声音
There it is again.
这里不太对劲  太奇怪了
Something's not right here. Not right at all.
你刚说话了  用树语
You just said something... Treeish.
才没有  我就伸了个懒腰
No, I didn't. I was just stretching.
你高了
You're taller.
-谁  -你啊
- Who? - You!
-怎比高了  -比我高了
- Than what? - Than me!
我一直比你高
I've always been taller than you.
皮平  大家都知道我高  你矮
Pippin, everyone knows I'm the tall one. You're the short one.
拜托  梅里
Please, Merry.
你多高  最多三尺六吧
You're what? Three-foot-six? At the most?
看看我  都快三尺七了
Whereas me, I'm pushing 3'7".
三尺八
3'8"!
都有三尺八了
Three-foot-eight.
你耍什么花招了
You did something.
梅里  别  别喝
Merry, don't! Don't drink it!
梅里
Merry!
别这样  树须说你不能喝
No, Treebeard said that you shouldn't have any.
-我也要  -有危险
- I want some! - It could well be dangerous!
还我  梅里
Give me it back. Merry!
怎么回事
What's happening?!
它夹住我脚了
It's got my leg!
梅里
Merry!
救命
Help!
滚开
Away with you.
你不该醒
You should not be waking.
吃泥土  挖深洞  喝神水
Eat earth. Dig deep. Drink water.
睡去吧
Go to sleep.
快走
Away with you.
上来  森林正在苏醒
Come, the forest is waking up.
这里危险
It isn't safe.
树木开始失去理智
The trees have grown wild and dangerous.
怒火腐蚀了心灵
Anger festers in their hearts.
黑暗侵蚀了思想
Black are their thoughts.
仇恨之火熊熊燃烧
Strong is their hate.
可以的话  他们会伤害你们
They will harm you if they can.
现在我的同类太少了
There are too few of us now.
恩特(树人)太少  看不好他们
Too few of us Ents left to manage them.
为什么你活了这么久  同类还这么少
Why are there so few of you when you have lived so long?
-没有小恩特(树人)吗  -[恩特(树人)语]
- Are there Ent children? - Bru-ra-hroom.
已经很多年没有恩特(树人)宝宝了
There have been no Entings for a terrible long count of years.
为什么
Why is that?
树妻都没有了
We lost the Entwives.
真抱歉
Oh, I'm sorry.
-她们怎么死的  -死  不
- How did they die? - Die? No.
她们不见了
We lost them.
现在我们找不到她们了
And now we cannot find them.
你们在夏尔也没见过树妻吧
I don't suppose you've seen Entwives in the Shire?
应该没见过
Can't say that I have.
你呢  皮皮
You, Pip?
她们长什么样
What do they look like?
我也不记得了
I don't remember now.
埃多拉斯  美杜塞尔德的金殿
Edoras and the Golden Hall of Meduseld.
洛汗国  希奥顿王的御所
There dwells Theoden, King of Rohan...
他的心智已被控制
whose mind is overthrown.
萨茹曼牢牢地掌控着希奥顿王
Saruman's hold over King Theoden is now very strong.
王上  您的儿子
My lord, your son...
他逝去了
he is dead.
王上
My lord?
叔叔
Uncle?
您就不去看看他吗
Will you not go to him?
您就这样无动于衷吗
Will you do nothing?
说话要小心
Be careful what you say.
别指望这儿的人会欢迎我们
Do not look for welcome here.
他一定是夜里过世的
Oh, he must have died sometime in the night.
一夜失去独子和继承人
What a tragedy for the king...
王上是多么不幸
to lose his only son and heir.
我能理解  他的离世很难接受
I understand. His passing is hard to accept.
尤其现在你哥哥也弃你不顾
Especially now that your brother has deserted you.
离我远点  小人
Leave me alone, snake!
但你的确是孤身一人
Oh, but you are alone.
当夜阑人静  长夜漫漫
Who knows what you've spoken to the darkness,
个中苦味又能向谁诉说
in the bitter watches of the night,
当你的生命渐渐消逝
when all your life seems to shrink,
寝宫的围墙步步紧逼
and the walls of your bower closing in about you,
不断压抑着你那崇尚自由的灵魂
a hutch to trammel some wild thing in.
如此美丽
So fair.
如此冰冷
So cold.
如同黯淡春日的清晨
Like a morning of pale spring...
依然透着冬日的料峭
still clinging to winter's chill.
你的话就是毒药
Your words are poison.
墓地都没这么沉闷
You'll find more cheer in a graveyard.
见吾王之前
I cannot allow you before
请卸下你们的武器  灰袍甘道夫
Theoden King so armed, Gandalf Greyhame.
这是奉巧言格里马之命
By order of Grima Wormtongue.
您的手杖
Your staff.
你不会连老人家的拐杖也要拿走吧
You would not part an old man from his walking stick.
王上  灰袍巫师甘道夫来了
My lord, Gandalf the Grey is coming.
他只会带来坏消息
He's a herald of woe.
你最近的待客之道可有所退步啊
The courtesy of your hall is somewhat lessened of late...
希奥顿王
Theoden King.
他不招人待见
He's not welcome.
我为什么要欢迎你
Why should I welcome you...
乌鸦嘴甘道夫
Gandalf Stormcrow?
问得好  王上
A just question, my liege.
偏偏这么晚了
Late is the hour...
巫师不请自来
in which this conjurer chooses to appear.
我称他为噩耗使者
Lathspell I name him.
来者不善  善者不来
Ill news is an ill guest.
闭嘴  管住你爱煽风点火的舌头
Be silent. Keep your forked tongue behind your teeth.
我历经烈火和死亡的考验
I have not passed through fire and death...
不是为了听你这蠢货嚼舌根
to bandy crooked words with a witless worm.
他的手杖
His staff.
我不是说  要你们没收巫师的手杖
I told you to take the wizard's staff.
希奥顿
Theoden,
森格尔之子
son of Thengel,
你在魔影中沉沦太久
too long have you sat in the Shadows.
我要是你  就乖乖不动
I would stay still if I were you.
请听我说
Hearken to me!
我来解救你
I release you...
脱离邪恶的咒语
from the spell.
你在这无法施展法力
You have no power here...
灰袍甘道夫
Gandalf the Grey.
萨茹曼  快快脱离  毒液离开伤口
I will draw you, Saruman, as poison is drawn from a wound.
等等
Wait.
我走了  希奥顿就会死
If I go, Theoden dies.
你杀不了我
You did not kill me...
也杀不了他
you will not kill him.
洛汗国是我的
Rohan is mine.
快走
Be gone.
我认得你
I know your face.
伊奥温
Eowyn.
甘道夫
Gandalf?
我的朋友  再一次呼吸自由的空气吧
Breathe the free air again, my friend.
近来我的梦一直被黑暗笼罩
Dark have been my dreams of late.
重新持剑
Your fingers would remember their old strength better,
你将重获力量
if they grasped your sword.
我从来
I've only...
一直只效忠于您  王上
ever served you, my lord.
你的妖术曾把我当成
Your leechcraft would have
苟延残喘的畜生一般使唤
had me crawling on all fours like a beast!
请别赶我走
Send me not from your sight.
不要  王上  切莫动手
No, my lord! No, my lord.
让他走
Let him go.
因为他的缘故  已经害太多人流血
Enough blood has been spilt on his account.
都给我滚开
Get out of my way!
吾王希奥顿万岁
Hail, Theoden King!
希奥杰德在哪里
Where is Theodred?
我儿呢
Where is my son?
高贵的勇士战死沙场
Bealocwealm hafae fréone frecan forth onsended
悲歌轻吟  痛悼哀伤
giedd sculon singan gléomenn sorgiende
美杜塞尔德之士  今已不在
on Meduselde þæt he ma no wære
吾王的挚爱之子
his dryhtne dyrest and mæga deorost.
永远安息
Bealo...
永志花
Simbelmyn?
一直盛开在先王们的安息之处
Ever has it grown on the tombs of my forbearers.
而今吾儿的墓地也遍布此花
Now it shall cover the grave of my son.
这悲惨的归宿本该属于我
Alas that these evil days should be mine.
少者湮灭  老者残存
The young perish and the old linger.
我本该在有生之年
That I should live
看着这个家族繁盛
to see the last days of my house.
希奥杰德之死不是你的错
Theodred's death was not of your making.
白发人不该送黑发人
No parent should have to bury their child.
他是个坚强的人
He was strong in life.
他的灵魂定将与先王们同在
His spirit will find its way to the halls of your fathers.
安眠吧
Westu hál.
安息吧  希奥杰德  安息吧
Fereu, Théodred, Fereu.
没有警告
They had no warning.
他们手无寸铁
They were unarmed.
蛮人穿过西伏尔德
Now the Wild Men are moving
长驱直入  一路放火
through the Westfold, burning as they go.
干草  房屋  树木无一幸免
Rick, cot and tree.
妈妈在哪儿
Where is Mama?
这只是萨茹曼毁灭的冰山一角
This is but a taste of the terror that Saruman will unleash.
一旦他与索隆联手  那才更可怕
All the more potent for he is driven now by fear of Sauron.
抗击敌军  与他正面交锋
Ride out and meet him head on.
别让他伤害女人们和孩子
Draw him away from your women and children.
你必须战斗
You must fight.
此刻两千精兵向北挺进
You have 2000 good men riding north as we speak.
伊奥梅尔仍对你忠心耿耿
Eomer is loyal to you.
他的士兵会回来  为国王而战
His men will return and fight for their king.
他们距此有三百里格之遥
They will be 300 leagues from here by now.
伊奥梅尔帮不了我们
Eomer cannot help us.
我知道你们对我的期望
I know what it is you want of me...
但我不会再给子民带来任何伤亡
but I will not bring further death to my people.
我不会冒险开战
I will not risk open war.
战争已然打响  不管你想不想冒险
Open war is upon you, whether you would risk it or not.
据我所知
When last I looked...
洛汗国王是希奥顿  不是阿拉贡
Theoden, not Aragorn, was king of Rohan.
那国王的最终决定是什么
Then what is the king's decision?
奉国王之命
By order of the king...
全城人员撤离
the city must empty.
撤至海尔姆深谷避难
We make for the refuge of Helm's Deep.
不要被钱物所累
Do not burden yourself with treasures.
仅带生活必需品
Take only what provisions you need.
海尔姆深谷
Helm's Deep.
该挺身战斗的时候  他们却躲到山林
They flee to the mountains when they should stand and fight.
国王不出来抵抗  谁还会挺身而出
Who will defend them if not their king?
他也是从子民利益考虑
He's only doing what he thinks is best for his people.
海尔姆深谷从前救过他们的命
Helm's Deep has saved them in the past.
那条峡谷是死胡同
There is no way out of that ravine.
希奥顿是自找死路
Theoden is walking into a trap.
他以为那里最安全
He thinks he's leading them to safety.
但等待他们的会是大屠杀
What they will get is a massacre.
希奥顿固执己见  我为他担忧
Theoden has a strong will, but I fear for him.
我为洛汗国的生死存亡担忧
I fear for the survival of Rohan.
他最终还是需要你  阿拉贡
He will need you before the end, Aragorn.
洛希尔人民需要你
The people of Rohan will need you.
我们必须守住防线
The defenses have to hold.
会守住的
They will hold.
灰袍圣徒
The Grey Pilgrim.
他们以前就这么叫我
That's what they used to call me.
按人类的时间算
Three hundred lives of Men
我已活了三百辈子  可现在时间却不多了
I've walked this earth, and now I have no time.
但愿这趟我能搬得到救兵
With luck, my search will not be in vain.
待我五天后  迎着第一道曙光出现
Look to my coming at first light on the fifth day.
黎明之际  眺望东方
At dawn, look to the east.
去吧
Go.
这马快疯了  大人
That horse is half mad, my lord.
你没办法的  别管它了
There's nothing you can do. Leave him.
嘘  快安静
Fæste, stille nú,
快安静
Fæste, stille nú.
大战即将来临
Lac is drefed, gefrægon.
你叫什么名字
Hwæt nemnað ðe? Hm? Hwæt nemnað ðe?
它叫布雷戈
His name is Brego.
是我堂哥的马
He was my cousin's horse.
布雷戈
Brego.
你的名字充满王者之气
Din nama is cynglic.
你在担心什么  布雷戈
Man le trasta, Brego?
你看到了什么
Man cenich?
我对精灵的魔法略有耳闻
I have heard of the magic of Elves...
但我没想到北方游侠也会
but I did not look for it in a Ranger from the North.
你说得就和精灵一样流利
You speak as one of their own.
我在幽谷长大
I was raised in Rivendell...
曾经
for a time.
把它放了吧
Turn this fellow free.
它该从战场退下了
He's seen enough of war.
白袍甘道夫
Gandalf the White.
愚人甘道夫
Gandalf the Fool!
他以为晋升为白袍就能扳倒我吗
Does he seek to humble me with his newfound piety?
那个巫师还有三个同伴
There were three who followed the wizard.
一个精灵  一个矮人和一个人类
An Elf, a Dwarf and a Man.
你浑身恶臭
You stink of horse.
那个人类
The Man...
是来自刚铎吗
was he from Gondor?
不  从北方来
No, from the North.
貌似杜内丹游侠
One of the Dunedain Rangers, I thought he was.
他衣衫褴褛
His cloth was poor.
戴有一枚奇怪的戒指
And yet he bore a strange ring.
绿宝石作眼的两条大蛇
Two serpents with emerald eyes.
一条张着血盆大口  另一条用金花作冠
One devouring, the other crowned with golden flowers.
巴拉希尔之戒
The Ring of Barahir.
灰袍甘道夫以为找到了伊熙尔杜的后嗣
So Gandalf Greyhame thinks he has found Isildur's heir.
失落的刚铎国王  他太天真了
The lost king of Gondor. He is a fool.
王族之脉多年前早已灭亡
The line was broken years ago.
这无关紧要
It matters not.
人类世界即将毁灭
The world of Men shall fall.
就从埃多拉斯开始
It will begin at Edoras.
我准备好了  甘姆林
I am ready, Gamling.
把马牵来
Bring my horse.
这不是败退
This is not a defeat.
我们还会回来
We will return.
一定会
你的剑术不错
You have some skill with a blade.
这里的女人很早就知道
Women of this country learned long ago:
即便无剑在身也会死于剑下
those without swords can still die upon them.
我不惧怕死亡和伤痛
I fear neither death nor pain.
那你怕什么  公主
What do you fear, my lady?
牢笼
A cage.
困在铁栏之内  直至终老
To stay behind bars until use and old age accept them.
英勇奋战仅成追忆奢望
And all chance of valor has gone beyond recall or desire.
你是王族之女
You're a daughter of kings...
也是洛汗的女战士
a shieldmaiden of Rohan.
这不会是你的命运
I do not think that would be your fate.
希奥顿不会待在埃多拉斯
Theoden will not stay at Edoras.
那里不堪一击  他深知这点
It's vulnerable. He knows this.
他料到那座城会被攻陷
He will expect an attack on the city.
他们会逃往海尔姆深谷
They will flee to Helm's Deep...
洛汗王国的要塞
the great fortress of Rohan.
跋涉崎岖的山路
It is a dangerous road to take through the mountains.
加上女人和孩子
They will be slow.
他们肯定走不快
They will have women and children with them.
派出你的座狼骑兵
Send out your Warg-riders.
讨厌鬼  别走太远
Hey, stinker, don't go getting too far ahead.
-你干嘛这样  -怎么了
- Why do you do that? - What?
一直骂他  羞辱他
Call him names. Run him down all the time.
因为
Because.
因为他就是这样  弗罗多先生
Because that's what he is, Mr. Frodo.
他满口谎言  无信无义
There's naught left in him but lies and deceit.
他只想要魔戒  他只关心这个
It's the Ring he wants. It's all he cares about.
你知道魔戒对他的折磨吗
You have no idea what it did to him...
现在还深受影响
what it's still doing to him.
我想帮他  山姆
I want to help him, Sam.
为什么
Why?
我相信他会改邪归正
Because I have to believe he can come back.
你救不了他  弗罗多先生
You can't save him, Mr. Frodo.
你知道什么  一无所知
What do you know about it? Nothing!
对不起  山姆  我不知道为什么会这样
I'm sorry, Sam. I don't know why I said that.
我知道
I do.
因为魔戒
It's the Ring.
你的眼神都离不开它
You can't take your eyes off it.
我见过你那样子
I've seen you.
你寝食难安
You're not eating. You barely sleep.
它在吞噬你  弗罗多先生
It's taken hold of you, Mr. Frodo.
-你要抵抗  -我明白我该怎么做  山姆
- You have to fight it. - I know what I have to do, Sam.
魔戒托付给了我  这是我的使命
The Ring was entrusted to me. It's my task.
我的  我一个人的
Mine! My own!
听听你说的话
Can't you hear yourself?
你知道你像谁吗
Don't you know who you sound like?
我们需要它
We wants it.
我们要得到它
We needs it.
一定要得到宝贝
Must have the precious.
他们从我们这里偷走
They stole it from us.
卑鄙无耻的霍比特人
Sneaky little Hobbitses.
邪恶  狡诈  虚伪
Wicked. Tricksy. False.
不  主人不是这样
No. Not master.
就是这样  宝贝  虚伪
Yes, precious. False.
他们欺骗你  伤害你  满口谎言
They will cheat you, hurt you, lie!
主人是我的朋友
Master's my friend.
你没有朋友  没人喜欢你
You don't have any friends. Nobody likes you.
我不听  我不要听
Not listening. I'm not listening.
你是个骗子  小偷
You're a liar and a thief.
不是
No.
杀人犯
Murderer.
滚开
Go away.
要我滚
Go away?
我讨厌你
I hate you.
我恨你
要是没有我  你又在哪  咕噜  咕噜
Where would you be without me? Gollum. Gollum.
是我救了我们
I saved us.
多亏了我  能活下来都是因为我
It was me. We survived because of me.
不再是了
Not anymore.
你说什么
What did you say?
现在有主人照顾我们
Master looks after us now.
不需要你
We don't need you.
什么
What?
走开
Leave now...
永远别回来
and never come back.
不
No.
走开  永远别回来
Leave now and never come back.
Leave now and never come back!
我让他滚开
We told him to go away.
他就走了  宝贝
And away he goes, precious.
他走了  他走了
Gone! Gone! Gone!
斯密戈自由了
Smeagol is free!
看
Look.
看  这是斯密戈找到的
Look. See what Smeagol finds?
还是幼崽
They are young.
鲜嫩  美味
They are tender. They are nice.
没错没错  快吃掉  吃掉
Yes, they are. Eat them. Eat them!
你这是让他恶心
You'll make him sick, you will...
看看你
behaving like that.
小兔子只有一种吃法
There's only one way to eat a brace of coneys.
你干什么
What's it doing?
又愚又肥的霍比特人
Stupid, fat Hobbit.
你把美味毁了
It ruins it.
毁什么了  它们的肉少得可怜
What's to ruin? There's hardly any meat on them.
只差上好的洋芋了
What we need is a few good taters.
洋芋是什么  宝贝
What's taters, precious?
什么是洋芋
What's taters? Eh?
马  铃  薯
Po-ta-toes.
用水煮  捣碎  慢慢炖
Boil them, mash them, stick them in a stew.
一大盘金灿灿的薯条  再加上一条烤鱼
Lovely, big, golden chips with a nice piece of fried fish.
就连你也会忍不住口水
Even you couldn't say no to that.
才不会
Oh, yes, we could.
坏了条好鱼
Spoil a nice fish.
要是给我们
Give it to us raw...
就会生吃  撕咬
and wriggling.
吃你的恶心薯条
You keep nasty chips.
无可救药
You're hopeless.
弗罗多先生
Mr. Frodo?
-他们是谁  -恶人
- Who are they? - Wicked men.
索隆的走狗
Servants of Sauron.
他们被召唤去魔多
They are called to Mordor.
黑暗魔君正在召集所有部队
The Dark One is gathering all armies to him.
用不了多久  就会准备就绪
It won't be long now. He will soon be ready.
-准备好干嘛  -发动战争
- Ready to do what? - To make his war.
将整个世界笼罩在魔影中
The last war that will cover all the world in Shadow.
我们得快点行动  快  山姆
We've got to get moving. Come on, Sam.
弗罗多先生
Mr. Frodo.
看
Look.
是毛象
It's an oliphaunt.
家乡的人不会相信我们的所见所闻
No one at home will believe this.
斯密戈
Smeagol?
我们逗留得太久了
We've lingered here too long.
快点  山姆
Come on, Sam.
等等  我们是无辜的路人
Wait! We're innocent travelers!
这片土地上没有路人
There are no travelers in this land.
只有黑暗之塔的奴仆
Only servants of the Dark Tower.
我们有秘密任务在身
We are bound to an errand of secrecy.
我们面临同样的敌人
Those that claim to oppose
没必要为难我们
the enemy would do well not to hinder us.
敌人
The enemy?
我想他的使命感也不比你差
His sense of duty was no less than yours, I deem.
他叫什么名字
You wonder what his name is...
来自何方
where he came from.
是不是个十足的坏人
And if he was really evil at heart.
谎言和胁迫让他离家远征
What lies or threats led him on this long march from home.
他是否愿意在此...
If he would not rather have stayed there...
长眠
in peace.
我们终将是战争牺牲品
War will make corpses of us all.
把他们绑起来
Bind their hands.
这倒是真的  你们很少看到女矮人
It's true, you don't see many Dwarf women.
因为矮人们的声音和长相都差不多
And in fact, they are so alike in voice and appearance...
经常被误认为是男矮人
that they're often mistaken for Dwarf men.
女矮人也有胡须
It's the beards.
所以  给大家造成一种错觉
This, in turn, has given rise to the belief...
没有女矮人
that there are no Dwarf women...
小矮人们是从石头缝里蹦出来的...
and that Dwarves just spring out of holes in the ground...
这当然荒谬极了
which is, of course, ridiculous.
没关系  不要慌张
It's all right. Nobody panic.
刚是故意的  我故意的
That was deliberate. It was deliberate.
很久没看到我侄女笑这么大声了
I haven't seen my niece smile for a long time.
她还是个小女孩时  父亲就去世了
She was a girl when they brought her father back dead.
被奥克砍死的
Cut down by Orcs.
她看着母亲悲伤过度而病逝
She watched her mother succumb to grief.
之后就孤身一人惶恐度日
Then she was left alone,
还要照料她的国王
to tend her king in growing fear.
孤苦地守在一个
Doomed to wait upon an old man
本该像父亲一样疼爱她的老人身边
who should have loved her as a father.
吉姆利
Gimli.
不  我不能喝
No, I couldn't.
真的不必了
I really couldn't.
我炖了些汤
I made some stew.
不是很多  但是热的
It isn't much, but it's hot.
谢谢
Thank you.
-很好喝  -真的吗
- It's good. - Really?
叔叔告诉我一件奇怪的事
My uncle told me a strange thing.
他说你曾和我的祖父  森格尔并肩作战
He said that you rode to war with Thengel, my grandfather.
他肯定弄错了
But he must be mistaken.
希奥顿王的记性很好
King Theoden has a good memory.
他那时才是个小孩
He was only a small child at the time.
那你起码有六十岁了
Then you must be at least 60.
难道七十
Seventy?
你不可能有八十岁
But you cannot be 80!
八十七岁
Eighty-seven.
你是杜内丹人
You are one of the Dunedain.
努门诺尔后裔  拥有长久的生命
A descendant of Numenor, blessed with long life.
传言你的种族已成为传说
It was said that your race had passed into legend.
幸存者很少
There are few of us left.
北部王国早已灭亡
The Northern Kingdom was destroyed long ago.
对不起  请吃吧
I'm sorry. Please, eat.
乌多米尔之光永不消退
The light of the Evenstar does not wax and wane.
这是我的选择
It is mine to give to whom I will.
吾心所属
Like my heart.
安稳地睡吧
Go to sleep.
我已入眠
I am asleep.
这是梦
This is a dream.
是个美梦
Then it is a good dream.
睡吧
Sleep.
你曾说
Minlû pedich nin
这一天终将来临
i aur hen telitha.
这只是个开始
ú i vethed na i onnad.
和弗罗多一起去  是你的必经之路
Boe bedich go Frodo. Han bâd lîn.
我看不清要走的路
Dolen i vâd o nin.
路就在你的脚下
Si peliannen i vad na dail lin.
你不该犹豫
Si boe ú-dhannathach.
阿尔玟
Arwen...
如果你无以相信
Ae ú-esteliach nad,
请相信乌多米尔
estelio han,
相信我们的感情
estelio ammen.
她在哪里
Where is she?
送你项链的女人
The woman who gave you that jewel.
我们的时代结束了
Our time here is ending.
阿尔玟的时间也不多了
Arwen's time is ending.
放她走吧
Let her go.
让她乘船西去
Let her take the ship into the west.
让她带着对你的爱去往阿门洲
Let her bear away her love for you to the Undying Lands.
那里时光永驻
There it will be ever green.
但那都是回忆
But never more than memory.
我不会让我女儿在这等死
I will not leave my daughter here to die.
她留下来是因为还有希望
She stays because she still has hope.
她留下来是为了你
She stays for you.
她该和她的族人在一起
She belongs with her people.
你就打算这样走吗
Nach gwannatha sin?
你以为趁天不亮就能悄悄走掉吗
Ma nathach hi gwannathach or minuial archened?
我不会再回来
ú-ethelithon.
你太低估了你的能力
Estelio guru lîn ne dagor.
你定会凯旋
Ethelithach.
我并非指战死沙场
ú-bedin o gurth ne dagor.
那你指什么
O man pedich?
你有机会过新的生活
Edra le men, men na guil edwen,
远离硝烟  悲伤和绝望
haer o auth a nîr a naeth.
为什么这么说
Why are you saying this?
我是凡人  而你是精灵
I am mortal. You are Elf-kind.
这是个梦  阿尔玟
It was a dream, Arwen.
仅此而已
Nothing more.
我不信
I don't believe you.
这是属于你的
This belongs to you.
这是送给你的
It was a gift.
留着吧
Keep it.
大人
My lord?
她和她的族人
She is sailing to the undying Lands
坐船去了阿门洲
with all that is left of her kin.
那是什么
What is it?
-哈马  -我不确定
- Hama? - I'm not sure.
座狼
Wargs!
是侦察兵
A scout!
那是什么  你看到了什么
What is it? What do you see?
是座狼  我们遇袭了
Warg! We're under attack!
带他们快离开
Get them out of here!
所有骑兵上前
All riders to the head of the column.
快  扶我上去  我也是骑兵
Come on. Get me up here. I'm a rider.
冲啊
Come on!
你带大家去海尔姆深谷  快点
You must lead the people to Helm's Deep, and make haste.
-我也能参战  -不行
- I can fight. - No!
你必须得去  就当是为了我
You must do this, for me.
跟着我
Follow me!
-向前  我说  向前冲锋  -往低处跑
- Forward. I mean, charge forward. - Make for the lower ground!
-行了  走吧  -跟紧点  别走散
- That's it! Go on! - Stay together!
尝尝我斧头的厉害
Bring your pretty face to my ax.
这个算我的
That one counts as mine!
臭烘烘的怪物
Stinking creature.
阿拉贡
Aragorn!
Aragorn?
快说  我让你死个痛快
Tell me what happened and I will ease your passing.
他
He's...
死了
dead.
他滚下了山崖
He took a little tumble off the cliff.
你胡说
You lie.
把伤员抬上马
Get the wounded on horses.
艾森加德的狼随时会回来
The wolves of Isengard will return.
死的留下
Leave the dead.
走吧
Come.
-终于到了  -海尔姆深谷
- At last! - Helm's Deep.
到了到了  海尔姆深谷
There it is, Helm's Deep.
我们安全了
We're safe!
我们安全了  公主
We're safe, my lady.
谢谢
Thank you.
-妈妈  -伊奥泰因
- Mama! - Eothain!
弗蕾达
Freda!
-其余食物呢  -这就是所有食物了  公主
- Where is the rest? - This is all we could save, my lady.
搬进洞里
Take it to the caves.
国王驾到
Make way for the king.
希奥顿王驾到  快让道
Make way for Theoden. Make way for the king.
这么少  只回来这么几个人
So few. So few of you have returned.
我们的人民安全了
Our people are safe.
为此牺牲了很多条性命
We have paid for it with many lives.
公主
My lady.
阿拉贡大人呢
Lord Aragorn...
他在哪里
where is he?
他跌下了山崖
He fell.
所有兵力在城墙内集合
Draw all our forces behind the wall.
封住城门  哨兵放哨
Bar the gate. And set a watch on the surround.
王上  不能战斗的人怎么办
What of those who cannot fight, my lord?
妇女和孩子
The women and children?
让他们待在洞里
Get them into the caves.
萨茹曼要想攻进来
Saruman's arm will have grown long indeed
可没这么简单
if he thinks he can reach us here.
海尔姆深谷只有一个弱点
Helm's Deep has one weakness.
它的外墙岩石坚不可摧
Its outer wall is solid rock...
但地下有条狭窄的暗渠
but for a small culvert at its base...
差不多排水沟大小
which is little more than a drain.
火怎么烧的化石砖
How? How can fire undo stone?
什么武器能击垮石墙
What kind of device could bring down the wall?
只要城墙缺裂  海尔姆深谷就会沦陷
If the wall is breached, Helm's Deep will fall.
就算城墙崩塌
Even if it is breached,
也需数千兵力
it would take a number beyond reckoning thousands
才能攻下堡垒
to storm the Keep.
是数万兵力
Tens of thousands.
但是大人  我们兵力恐怕不够
But, my lord, there is no such force.
新势力正在崛起
A new power is rising.
胜利唾手可得
Its victory is at hand.
今晚
This night...
洛希尔人将血染这片土地
the land will be stained with the blood of Rohan!
向海尔姆深谷进军
March to Helm's Deep!
不留一个活口
Leave none alive!
开战
To war!
人类将看不到明日的曙光
There will be no dawn for Men.
看  南边有烟
Look. There's smoke to the south.
这几天艾森加德
There is always smoke rising...
总有烟雾升起
from Isengard these days.
艾森加德
Isengard?
从前
There was a time...
萨茹曼还会来我的森林走走
when Saruman would walk in my woods.
而现在的他
But now he has a mind of metal...
满脑子钢筋铁器
and wheels.
他不再在意生命
He no longer cares for growing things.
那是什么
What is it?
萨茹曼的大军
It's Saruman's army.
战争开始了
The war has started.
愿维拉的神恩保佑你
May the grace of the Valar protect you.
布雷戈
Brego.
阿尔玟
Arwen.
是时候了
Tollen i lû.
船将驶向维林诺  走吧  还为时未晚
I chair gwannar na Valannor. Si bado, no círar.
我心已定
I have made my choice.
他不会回来了
He is not coming back.
希望已破灭  为何你还在此流连
Why do you linger here when there is no hope?
希望还在
There is still hope.
就算阿拉贡战后活下来  你们还是会分开
If Aragorn survives this war, you will still be parted.
就算索隆战败  阿拉贡称王
If Sauron is defeated and Aragorn made king...
你所有愿望成真
and all that you hope for comes true...
你还是要忍受凡人生命有限的痛苦
you will still have to taste the bitterness of mortality.
无论是利剑  还是时间
Whether by the sword or the slow decay of time...
阿拉贡终究难逃一死
Aragorn will die.
你将无以慰藉
And there will be no comfort for you...
只有看他离去的无尽痛苦
no comfort to ease the pain of his passing.
他会走向死亡
He will come to death...
以人皇的光辉形象
an image of the splendor of the kings of Men in glory
永驻人们的心间
undimmed before the breaking of the world.
但是你  我的女儿
But you, my daughter...
你会永远活在黑暗之中
you will linger on in darkness and in doubt...
一如没有星辰的冬夜
as nightfall in winter that comes without a star.
你将踟蹰于此
Here you will dwell...
在渐逝的树木之下细数哀伤
bound to your grief under the fading trees...
直到世界换颜
until all the world is changed...
你不灭的生命都将如此度过
and the long years of your life are utterly spent.
阿尔玟
Arwen.
这里一无所有
There is nothing for you here...
只有死亡
only death.
难道你不爱我了吗
Ah im, ú-'erin veleth lîn?
我爱您  父王
Gerich veleth nîn, ada.
世界变了
I amar prestar aen,
我从流水中感知到
han mathon ne nen,
我从土壤中感知到
han mathon ne chae,
我从空气中嗅到
a han noston ned 'wilith.
敌人的势力日益强大
The power of the enemy is growing.
索隆会利用他的傀儡萨茹曼
Sauron will use his puppet, Saruman...
消灭洛希尔人民
to destroy the people of Rohan.
艾森加德的魔军出动了
Isengard has been unleashed.
邪眼现已转向刚铎
The Eye of Sauron now turns to Gondor...
人类世界最后一片自由国度
the last free kingdom of Men.
战争会迅速蔓延到这个国度
His war on this country will come swiftly.
他感到至尊魔戒的靠近
He senses the Ring is close.
魔戒携带者的意志渐弱
The strength of the Ring-bearer is failing.
内心深处  弗罗多开始明白
In his heart, Frodo begins to understand...
这次征途将有去无回
the quest will claim his life.
你知道这一点
You know this.
你已预见
You have foreseen it.
我们必须冒这个险
It is the risk we all took.
黑暗聚集之地  魔戒的意志逐渐增强
In the gathering dark, the will of the Ring grows strong.
它努力想要回到人类的手上
It works hard now to find its way back into the hands of Men.
因为人类总是如此轻易受到蛊惑
Men, who are so easily seduced by its power.
年轻的刚铎将军只要一伸手
The young captain of Gondor has but to extend his hand...
将魔戒据为己有  世界就将沦陷
take the Ring for his own, and the world will fall.
这一时刻就快到了
It is close now.
它的目的就快达到
So close to achieving its goal.
索隆将主宰世间所有的生命
For Sauron will have dominion over all life on this Earth...
甚至到世界尽头
even unto to the ending of the world.
精灵的时代
The time of the Elves...
也将终结
is over.
我们眼看着中洲世界就此沉沦
Do we leave Middle-earth to its fate?
让他们孤军奋战  袖手旁观吗
Do we let them stand alone?
有什么消息
What news?
侦察兵报告说萨茹曼进攻洛汗
Our scouts report Saruman has attacked Rohan.
希奥顿的子民已逃往海尔姆深谷
Theoden's people have fled to Helm's Deep.
但我们也要守住自己的边境
But we must look to our own borders.
法拉米尔  奥克蠢蠢欲动
Faramir, Orcs are on the move.
索隆正在组建军团
Sauron is marshaling an army.
东方人和南方人的部队已到达魔栏农
Easterlings and Southrons are at the Black Gate.
-有多少  -几千  日渐增多
- How many? - Some thousands. More come every day.
谁防守北边河流
Who's covering the river to the north?
派了五百人在欧斯吉利亚斯
We pulled 500 men at Osgiliath.
如果这座城攻陷  我们就顶不住了
If their city is attacked, we won't hold it.
萨茹曼从艾森加德进攻
Saruman attacks from Isengard.
艾森加德
索隆从魔多进攻
Sauron from Mordor.
魔多
人类受到两面夹击
The fight will come to Men on both fronts.
刚铎势力单薄
Gondor is weak.
索隆很快会发起进攻
Sauron will strike us soon.
攻势猛烈
And he will strike hard.
他清楚我们现在无力还击
He knows now we do not have the strength to repel him.
米那斯提力斯
欧斯吉利亚斯
我的属下说你们是奥克的间谍
My men tell me that you are Orc spies.
间谍  省省吧
Spies? Now wait just a minute.
如果不是间谍  那你们是什么人
Well, if you're not spies, then who are you?
说
Speak.
我们是夏尔的霍比特人
We are Hobbits of the Shire.
我叫弗罗多·巴金斯
Frodo Baggins is my name,
他叫山姆怀斯·甘姆吉
and this is Samwise Gamgee.
你的保镖吗
Your bodyguard?
他的园丁
His gardener.
你们鬼鬼祟祟的朋友呢
And where is your skulking friend?
那个精瘦的东西
That gangrel creature.
看上去绝非善类
He had an ill-favored look.
没有其他人了
There was no other.
我们从幽谷出发  共有七人
We set out from Rivendell with seven companions.
一人在墨瑞亚牺牲
One we lost in Moria...
两人是我的同类
two were my kin...
还有一个矮人  一个精灵和两个人类
a Dwarf there was also. And an Elf and two Men.
阿拉松之子阿拉贡  以及刚铎的波洛米尔
Aragorn, son of Arathorn, and Boromir of Gondor.
你是波洛米尔的朋友
You're a friend of Boromir?
没错
Yes.
我认为是
For my part.
那听到他的死讯你一定不好过
It will grieve you then to learn that he is dead.
死了
Dead?
怎么死的  什么时候
How? When?
既然你是他的同伴
As one of his companions,
我倒希望你来告诉我
I'd hoped you would tell me.
如果波洛米尔出了事  请告诉我们
If something has happened to Boromir, we would have you tell us.
大约六天前
His horn washed up upon the riverbank,
他的号角被冲上河岸
about six days past.
裂成了两半
It was cloven in two.
不过我知道他已经不在人世了
But more than this, I know it in my heart.
他是我哥哥
He was my brother.
波洛米尔
Boromir!
这座城曾是我国的瑰宝
This city was once the jewel of our kingdom.
一块充满绮丽之景  欢乐与美乐之地
A place of light and beauty and music.
我们该让它重获昔日光彩
And so it shall be once more!
让魔多的敌人记住
Let the armies of Mordor know this:
这片土地将永不再落入敌手
Never again will the land of my people fall into enemy hands.
欧斯吉利亚斯重新属于刚铎
This city of Osgiliath has been reclaimed for Gondor!
-刚铎  -刚铎
- For Gondor! - For Gondor!
-刚铎万岁  -刚铎万岁
说得好  简短有力
Good speech. Nice and short.
得多留点时间豪饮
Leaves more time for drinking!
大家等不及了  快开酒
Break out the ale! These men are thirsty!
记住今天  弟弟
Remember today, little brother.
人生真惬意
Today, life is good.
怎么了
What?
他也在
He's here.
就不能给我们半刻安宁吗
One moment of peace, can he not give us that?
他在哪呢
Where is he?
刚铎最伟大的勇士  我的长子在哪
Where is Gondor's finest? Where's my first-born?
父亲
Father!
听说你几乎单枪匹马地击溃了敌军
They say you vanquished the enemy almost single-handedly.
没那么夸张  胜利也属于法拉米尔
They exaggerate. The victory belongs to Faramir also.
要不是他  这座城也不会失守
But for Faramir, this city would still be standing.
我不是派你守住的吗
Were you not entrusted to protect it?
本来可以守住  可惜我们寡不敌众
I would have done, but our numbers were too few.
人数不够
Oh, too few.
你放敌人进来为所欲为
You let the enemy walk in and take it on a whim.
总是成事不足败事有余
Always you cast a poor reflection on me.
我也不想这样
That is not my intent.
他一直努力让您满意  而您从不肯定他
You give him no credit, and yet he tries to do your will.
他爱您  父亲
He loves you, Father.
别提他的事
Do not trouble me with Faramir...
我清楚他有几斤几两
I know his uses, and they are few.
我们还有更要紧的事情要谈
We have more urgent things to speak of.
幽谷的埃尔隆德王要召开会议
Elrond of Rivendell has called a meeting.
没说原因  但我猜得出来
He will not say why, but I have guessed its purpose.
传言说  敌方的武器已经找到
It is rumored that the weapon of the enemy has been found.
至尊魔戒
The One Ring.
伊熙尔杜克星
Isildur's Bane.
现已落入精灵之手
It has fallen into the hands of the Elves.
人类  矮人  巫师都想占有
Everyone will try to claim it: Men, Dwarves, wizards.
魔戒不能落入他人之手
We cannot let that happen.
刚铎必须得到它
This thing must come to Gondor.
-刚铎  -我知道这很危险
- Gondor. - It's dangerous, I know.
意志不坚定的人会受到魔戒的蛊惑
Ever the Ring will seek to corrupt the hearts of lesser Men.
但是你意志坚定
But you, you are strong.
而且我们很需要它
And our need is great.
现在流血牺牲的
It is our blood which is being spilled,
都是我们的臣民
our people who are dying.
索隆正坐等时机
Sauron is biding his time.
召集新的部队
He's massing fresh armies.
他会回来的
He will return.
到时候  我们将无力阻止
And when he does, we will be powerless to stop him.
所以你必须去
You must go.
把那强大的礼物带给我
Bring me back this mighty gift.
不  我要和我的人民守在这里
No. My place is here with my people.
我不去幽谷
Not in Rivendell.
你怎么能违抗你的父亲
Would you deny your own father?
如果有需要
If there is need to go to Rivendell...
-就让我去吧  -你
- Send me in his stead. - You?
我明白了
Oh, I see.
这是刚铎的法拉米尔将军表现的好机会
A chance for Faramir, captain of Gondor, to show his quality.
我不这样认为
I think not.
这任务我只放心交给你哥哥
I trust this mission only to your brother.
只有他才不会让我失望
The one who will not fail me.
记住今天  弟弟
Remember today, little brother.
法拉米尔将军
Captain Faramir!
我们找到逃跑的那个了
We found the third one.
跟我走  快点
You must come with me. Now.
就在下面
Down there.
擅入禁忌之潭者格杀勿论
To enter the Forbidden Pool bears the penalty of death.
他们在等我下令
They wait for my command.
我该下令吗
Shall I shoot?
池水  岩石清又凉
The rock and pool is nice and cool.
鱼儿肥又鲜
So juicy sweet.
我们只想抓条鱼
Our only wish to catch a fish.
鱼儿肥又鲜
So juicy sweet.
等等
Wait.
它是我的人
This creature is bound to me.
我也需要它
And I to him.
它是我们的向导
He is our guide.
求你了
Please...
让我下去找它
let me go down to him.
斯密戈
Smeagol.
主人在这里
Master is here.
跟我来  斯密戈
Come, Smeagol.
相信主人  跟我来
Trust master. Come.
现在非要走吗
We must go now?
斯密戈  你要相信主人
Smeagol, you must trust master.
快跟我来
Follow me. Come on.
过来
Come.
跟我来  斯密戈
Come, Smeagol.
没错  斯密戈听话
Nice Smeagol. That's it.
跟我来
Come on.
别伤害它
Don't hurt him!
斯密戈  不要挣扎  听我说
Smeagol, don't struggle. Smeagol, listen to me.
主人
Master!
放开它
Let him off.
你要带他们去哪儿
Where're you leading them?
回答我
Answer me.
斯密戈
Smeagol.
为什么要哭  斯密戈
Why does it cry, Smeagol?
残忍的人类伤害了我们
Cruel Men hurts us.
主人欺骗了我们
Master tricksed us.
那当然了
Of course he did.
我早警告过你  他很狡猾
I told you he was tricksy.
他很虚伪
I told you he was false.
主人是我们的朋友
Master is our friend.
我们的朋友
Our friend.
主人背叛了我们
Master betrayed us.
不  这不关他的事
No. Not its business.
别管我们
Leave us alone!
卑鄙的小霍比特人
Filthy little Hobbitses!
他们偷了我们的东西
They stole it from us!
不  不
No. No.
他们偷走了什么
What did they steal?
我的宝贝
My precious!
我们得从这儿逃出去
We have to get out of here.
你快逃  现在就逃
You go. Go, now.
你能行的
You can do it.
弗罗多先生  利用魔戒
Use the Ring, Mr. Frodo.
就用这一次
Just this once.
戴上它
Put it on.
然后消失
Disappear.
我做不到
I can't.
你是对的  山姆
You were right, Sam.
你劝过我  但我
You tried to tell me but...
对不起
I'm sorry.
魔戒正在吞噬我  山姆
The Ring's taking me, Sam.
如果我戴上它
If I put it on...
他就会找到我
he'll find me.
他看得见
He'll see.
弗罗多先生
Mr. Frodo...
原来这就是一切谜团的答案
So this is the answer to all the riddles.
荒郊野外  你们两个半身人
Here in the Wild I have you...
落入我手中
two Halflings...
而我有一支忠诚的部队
and a host of men at my call.
至尊魔戒伸手可得
The Ring of Power within my grasp.
这是刚铎的法拉米尔将军
A chance for Faramir, captain of Gondor...
表现的好机会
to show his quality.
不
No!
快住手
Stop it!
放开他
Leave him alone.
你还不明白吗
Don't you understand?
他要摧毁这魔戒
He's got to destroy it!
所以我们要去魔多
That's where we're going, into Mordor.
去末日山
To the Mountain of Fire!
欧斯吉利亚斯遭到了攻击
Osgiliath is under attack.
请求支援
They call for reinforcements.
求你了  他肩负着重担
Please. It's such a burden.
帮帮他吧
Will you not help him?
将军
Captain?
准备出发
Prepare to leave.
把魔戒带去刚铎
The Ring will go to Gondor.
好样的  布雷戈  我的朋友
Mae carnen, Brego, mellon n?n.
-他还活着  -他在哪儿  在哪儿
- He's alive! - Where is he? Where is he?
闪开  我要灭了他
Get out of the way! I'm going to kill him!
你是我见过的最幸运  最谨慎
You are the luckiest, the canniest...
也是最鲁莽的家伙
and the most reckless man I ever knew.
祝福你  伙计
Bless you, laddie.
吉姆利  国王在哪儿
Gimli, where is the king?
你来迟了
Le abdollen.
你可真狼狈
You look terrible.
谢谢你
Hannon le.
你说敌军人数众多
A great host, you say.
艾森加德倾巢出动
All Isengard is emptied.
有多少
How many?
起码上万
Ten thousand strong at least.
上万
Ten thousand?
他们的目的只有一个
It is an army bred for a single purpose:
摧毁人类世界
To destroy the world of Men.
敌军日落前就能到达
They will be here by nightfall.
那就让它们来吧
Let them come!
全部士兵和能打仗的壮丁
I want every man and strong lad able to bear arms...
日落前做好战斗准备
to be ready for battle by nightfall.
我们从上方守住堤道和城门
We will cover the causeway and the gate from above.
深谷防御墙无人能破
No army has ever breached the Deeping Wall...
号角堡也从未让人攻入
or set foot inside the Hornburg!
这次来的不是乌合之众
This is no rabble of mindless Orcs.
是乌鲁克
These are Uruk-hai.
他们身着坚硬的铠甲  手持坚固的盾牌
Their armor is thick and their shields broad.
我也曾身经百战  矮人
I have fought many wars, Master Dwarf.
我知道怎么守住自己的要塞
I know how to defend my own keep.
这里坚若磐石易守难攻
They will break upon this fortress like water on rock.
萨茹曼的大军会烧杀抢掠
Saruman's hordes will pillage and burn.
他们以前就这样
We've seen it before.
庄稼可以再种
Crops can be resown...
房屋可以再建
homes rebuilt.
只要在这铜墙铁壁之内
Within these walls...
看谁耗得住谁
we will outlast them.
它们不是来毁坏洛汗的庄稼或是村庄
They do not come to destroy Rohan's crops or villages.
它们是来消灭人类
They come to destroy its people...
连孩子也不放过
down to the last child.
那你想我怎么样
What would you have me do?
看看我的子民
Look at my men.
他们都很害怕
Their courage hangs by a thread.
如果注定命绝于此
If this is to be our end,
我宁愿壮烈牺牲
then I would have them make such an end...
让世人永远铭记
as to be worthy of remembrance.
陛下  派骑兵吧
Send out riders, my lord.
你得求援
You must call for aid.
谁会来呢
And who will come?
精灵
Elves?
还是矮人
Dwarves?
我们可不像你  有那么多人相助
We are not so lucky in our friends as you.
昔日联盟不复存在
The old alliances are dead.
-刚铎会派援兵  -刚铎
- Gondor will answer. - Gondor?!
西伏尔德陷落的时候刚铎在哪里
Where was Gondor when the Westfold fell?!
我们被敌人围攻时刚铎在哪里
Where was Gondor when our enemies closed in around us?!
刚铎在哪...
Where was Gon...?
你错了  阿拉贡大人
No, my lord Aragorn...
我们孤军奋战
We are alone.
把妇女和孩子带进洞里
Get the women and children into the caves.
我们还要准备军粮...
We need more time to lay provisions...
没时间了  就要开战了
There is no time. War is upon us.
加固城门
Secure the gate.
我们恩特(树人)
We Ents have not troubled...
不参与人类和巫师之间的战争
about the wars of Men and wizards...
已经很久了
for a very long time.
但现在要发生的事
But now, something is about to happen...
已经有一个世纪
that has not happened...
没有发生过了
for an age.
恩特(树人)会议
Entmoot.
那是什么
What's that?
是集会
It is a gathering.
什么的聚会
A gathering of what?
山毛榉  橡树
Beech. Oak.
栗树  白杨树
Chestnut. Ash.
太好了
Good. Good. Good.
大家都来了
Many have come.
我们现在得商量
Now we must decide if the Ents...
恩特(树人)是否要参战
will go to war.
快进洞  躲进洞里
Move back! Move to the caves!
快点  大家动作快
Come on, people! Quickly, now!
把物资堆在墙边
We'll place the reserves along the wall.
这样可以接住坠落的弓箭手
They can support the archers from above the gate.
阿拉贡  你需要休息
Aragorn, you must rest.
你精疲力竭也帮不了我们
You're no use to us half alive.
阿拉贡
Aragorn!
要我和其他女人待在洞穴里
I'm to be sent with the women into the caves.
这任务很光荣
That is an honorable charge.
照顾孩子
To mind the children,
战士们回来了给他们安排吃住
to find food and bedding when the men return.
这算哪门子光荣
What renown is there in that?
公主  早晚有你的用武之地
My lady, a time may come for valor without renown.
当最后的防线攻破  人民又能依靠谁
Who then will your people look to in the last defense?
让我跟你并肩作战
Let me stand at your side.
这不是我能决定的
It is not in my power to command it.
你却没有让其他人留下
You do not command the others to stay!
他们跟你并肩作战是因为他们不愿跟你分开
They fight beside you because they would not be parted from you.
因为他们爱你
Because they love you.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
农民  蹄铁匠  马童
Farmers, farriers, stable boys.
都不是战士
These are no soldiers.
-不是年纪太大  -就是太小
- Most have seen too many winters. - Or too few.
看看他们  每个人都很害怕
Look at them. They're frightened.
眼里充满恐惧
I can see it in their eyes.
他们是以三百人对抗一万大军
Boe a hyn neled herain dan caer menig.
守在这里要比在埃多拉斯更有胜算
Si, beriathar hyn ammaeg na ned Edoras.
他们毫无胜算  阿拉贡
Aragorn, nedin dagor hen ú-'erir ortheri.
他们都是去送死
Natha daged dhaer!
那我就和他们一起死
Then I shall die as one of them!
让他去吧  伙计
Let him go, lad.
不要管他
Let him be.
能使剑的都去兵库领武器了
Every villager able to wield a sword has been sent to the armory.
王上
My lord?
我是谁  甘姆林
Who am I, Gamling?
您是我们的王  陛下
You are our king, sire.
那你相信你的国王吗
And do you trust your king?
您的子民  王上
Your men, my lord...
无论怎样都愿随您出生入死
will follow you to whatever end.
出生入死
To whatever end.
洛汗的骠骑在哪里
Where is the horse and the rider?
曾经吹响的号角在哪里
Where is the horn that was blowing?
他们就像落入山间的雨点
They have passed like rain on the mountains.
吹过草原的轻风般消逝不见
Like wind in the meadow.
那段戎马岁月已经西去
The days have gone down in the West...
消失在山的那边
behind the hills...
一去不复返
into Shadow.
怎么会这样
How did it come to this?
他们商议了那么久
It's been going for hours.
该有个结果了吧
They must have decided something by now.
结果  还早呢
Decided? No.
我们才刚刚
We only just finished saying...
问了早安
good morning.
可现在都是晚上了
But it's nighttime already.
你们还要商量多久
You can't take forever.
不要着急
Don't be hasty.
我们没时间了
We're running out of time!
快到外墙去  快
Move! Move to the outer wall.
把你的剑给我
Give me your sword.
你叫什么名字
What is your name?
哈烈斯  哈马之子  大人
Haleth, son of Hama, my lord.
他们说我们活不过今晚
The men are saying we will not live out the night.
他们说毫无希望
They say that it is hopeless.
这是把好剑
This is a good sword.
哈马之子  哈烈斯
Haleth, son of Hama...
希望永远存在
there is always hope.
我们一路追随你
We have trusted you this far.
你从未让我们失望
You have not led us astray.
请原谅我
Forgive me.
我不该绝望
I was wrong to despair.
没什么好原谅的  莱戈拉斯
ú-moe edaved, Legolas.
要是有时间  我要把这战袍改改
We had time, I'd get this adjusted.
胸口太紧
It's a little tight across the chest.
那不是奥克的号角
That is no Orc horn.
快去请国王
Send for the king.
-开城门  -打开城门
- Open the gate! - Open up the gate!
这怎么可能
How is this possible?
幽谷的埃尔隆德王让我带话
I bring word from Elrond of Rivendell.
精灵与人类曾经结盟
An alliance once existed between Elves and Men.
很久以前  我们并肩作战  同生共死
Long ago we fought and died together.
今日再次履行盟约
We come to honor that allegiance.
幸会  哈尔迪尔
Mae govannen, Haldir.
你们能来真是太好了
You are most welcome.
很荣幸再次与人类并肩作战
We are proud to fight alongside Men once more.
你也不给我挑个好地方
You could have picked a better spot.
伙计  不管你运气好坏
Well, lad, whatever luck you live by,
希望能撑得过今晚
let's hope it lasts the night.
你的朋友与你同在  阿拉贡
Your friends are with you, Aragorn.
希望他们也能撑过今晚
Let's hope they last the night.
别手下留情  敌人决不会手软
A Eruchîn, ú-dano i faelas a hyn an uben tanatha le faelas.
外面现在什么情况
What's happening out there?
你是要我跟你描述
Shall I describe it to you?
还是找个箱子给你垫着
Or would you like me to find you a box?
稳住
Dartho!
开战了
So it begins.
准备射击
Tangado a chadad!
它们的脖子和臂下防护最弱
Faeg i-varv dîn na lanc a nu ranc.
放箭
Hado i philinn!
他们射中了吗
Did they hit anything?
万箭齐发
Give them a volley.
-放箭  -放箭
- Fire! - Fire!
放箭雨
Hado ribed!
放马过来  来啊
Send them to me! Come on!
有梯子
Pendraith!
很好
Good!
拔剑
Swords! Swords!
莱戈拉斯  我干掉两个了
Legolas! Two already!
我这是第十七个
I'm on 17!
我绝不会让尖耳朵超过我
I'll have no pointy-ear outscoring me!
十九个
Nineteen!
梅里
Merry.
我们刚达成了一致
We have just agreed.
然后呢
Yes?
我在恩特(树人)会议上说了你们的名字
I have told your names to the Entmoot...
我们一致认为
and we have agreed...
你们不是奥克
you are not Orcs.
真是个好消息
Well, that's good news.
那萨茹曼呢
And what about Saruman?
你们商量的结果是什么
Have you come to a decision about him?
不要着急  梅里阿道克先生
Now, don't be hasty, Master Meriadoc.
不着急
Hasty?
我们的朋友正在浴血奋战
Our friends are out there.
需要我们的帮助
They need our help.
孤军奋战死路一条
They cannot fight this war on their own.
战争吗  没错
War? Yes.
战争会影响我们
It affects us all.
树干  树根  树枝
Tree, root and twig.
但你们必须明白   小霍比特人
But you must understand, young Hobbit...
用古恩特(树人)语交流
it takes a long time...
很费时间
to say anything in Old Entish...
除非是值得费时的事
and we never say anything...
否则我们
unless it is worth taking...
绝不会用古恩特(树人)语交流
a long time to say.
十七  十八
Seventeen! Eighteen!
十九
Nineteen!
二十
Twenty!
二十一
Twenty-one!
守住堤道
Causeway!
就这样吗
Is this it?
你就这点本事吗  萨茹曼
Is this is all you can conjure, Saruman?
把它拿下  莱戈拉斯
Togo hon dad, Legolas!
干掉它
Dago hon!
顶住城门
Brace the gate!
牵制它们  守住
Hold them! Stand firm!
阿拉贡
Aragorn!
吉姆利
Gimli!
放箭
Hado i philinn!
冲啊
Herio!
恩特(树人)不能阻止这场风暴
The Ents cannot hold back this storm.
只能一如既往地静观其变
We must weather such things as we have always done.
这就是你们商量的结果吗
How can that be your decision?!
这不是我们的战争
This is not our war.
但你们也属于这个世界
But you're part of this world!
不是吗
Aren't you?!
你们必须帮忙  拜托
You must help. Please.
你们一定要帮帮忙
You must do something.
梅里先生  你年轻又勇敢
You are young and brave, Master Merry.
但是你的任务完成了
But your part in this tale is over.
回家吧
Go back to your home.
也许树须说得对
Maybe Treebeard's right.
我们不属于这里  梅里
We don't belong here, Merry.
我们太过渺小
It's too big for us.
到头来  我们又能做些什么
What can we do in the end?
我们还有夏尔
We've got the Shire.
也许我们是该回家了
Maybe we should go home.
艾森加德的战火会蔓延开来
The fires of Isengard will spread...
塔克领和雄鹿地的森林也会被烧毁
and the woods of Tuckborough and Buckland will burn.
还有
And...
世上所有的绿色和一切的美好都会消失
And all that was once green and good in this world will be gone.
夏尔也将不复存在  皮平
There won't be a Shire, Pippin.
阿拉贡
Aragorn!
撤回城墙
Fall back to the Keep!
让大家撤退
Get your men out of there!
哈尔迪尔
Haldir!
快撤退
Nan barad!
你们干什么  为什么不打了
What are you doing? What are you stopping for?
快撤退
Nan barad!
哈尔迪尔
Haldir!
顶住城门
Brace the gate!
防住它们
Hold them!
去城门  准备战斗
To the gate. Draw your swords!
让开
Make way!
我们撑不了多久
We cannot hold much longer!
-防住它们  -你需要多久
- Hold them! - How long do you need?
能撑多久是多久
As long as you can give me.
吉姆利
Gimli!
拿木头来
Timbers!
顶住城门
Brace the gate!
上呀  我们灭了他们
Come on. We can take them.
这距离可不近
It's a long way.
把我丢过去
Toss me.
-什么  -我自己跳不过去
- What? - I cannot jump the distance!
你得把我丢过去
You'll have to toss me!
别告诉那个精灵
Don't tell the Elf.
绝对不会
Not a word.
顶住城门
Shore up the door!
-让开  -跟我过来
- Make way! - Follow me to the barricade.
注意后面
Watch our backs!
-再来一根  -拉高点
- Throw another one over here! - Higher!
把城门抵住
Hold fast the gate!
吉姆利  阿拉贡  快离开那儿
Gimli! Aragorn! Get out of there!
阿拉贡
Aragorn!
叫所有人撤退
Pull everybody back.
都撤退
Pull them back.
撤退
Fall back!
它们攻进来了
They have broken through!
城门被攻破了  撤退
The castle is breached. Retreat!
-撤退  -撤退
- Fall back! - Retreat!
快点进去  让大伙都进去
Hurry! Inside. Get them inside!
撤回堡里
Into the Keep!
我送你们到森林的西面边界
I will leave you at the western borders of the forest.
你们往北走  就可以回家了
You can make your way north to your homeland from there.
等等  停一下
Wait! Stop!
停一下
Stop!
掉头
Turn around.
-掉头  带我们去南边  -南边
- Turn around. Take us south. - South?
往南会经过艾森加德
But that will lead you past Isengard.
对呀  没错
Yes. Exactly.
往南走  我们可以悄悄绕过萨茹曼
If we go south, we can slip past Saruman unnoticed.
最危险的地方就是最安全的地方
The closer we are to danger, the farther we are from harm.
他绝对想不到
It's the last thing he'll expect.
我是想不明白
That doesn't make sense to me.
但是
But then...
你们个头小
you are very small.
也许可以
Perhaps you're right.
那就往南走吧
South it is, then.
坐好了  小夏尔人
Hold on, little Shirelings.
我就喜欢往南走
I always like going south.
就像下坡一样
Somehow it feels like going downhill.
你疯了吗  我们会被抓住
Are you mad? We'll be caught.
不  我们不会
No, we won't.
这次不会
Not this time.
你看
Look!
欧斯吉利亚斯在燃烧
Osgiliath burns!
魔多大军已经来了
Mordor has come.
魔戒救不了刚铎
The Ring will not save Gondor.
它只会摧毁刚铎
It has only the power to destroy.
求你了
Please...
放我走吧
let me go.
快走
Hurry.
法拉米尔
Faramir!
你必须放我走
You must let me go!
那几窝小田鼠
And those little family of field mice...
总爬到我身上  搞得我痒痒
that climb up sometimes, and they tickle me awfully.
它们总是想让我带它们去...
They're always trying to get somewhere where they...
这里许多树都曾是我朋友
Many of these trees were my friends.
从枝到叶都熟得不得了的老朋友
Creatures I had known from nut and acorn.
很遗憾  树须
I'm sorry, Treebeard.
它们都有自己的声音
They had voices of their own.
萨茹曼
Saruman.
作为巫师  你该更清楚
A wizard should know better!
你滔天的罪行
There is no curse in Elvish...
无论是精灵语  恩特(树人)语还是人类语
Entish or the tongues of Men...
都找不到词来谴责你
for this treachery.
看啊  那些树  它们都在移动
Look! The trees! They're moving!
它们要去哪儿
Where are they going?
他们要去找奥克算账
They have business with the Orcs.
今晚我要用石头
My business is with Isengard tonight...
攻塌艾森加德
with rock and stone.
太好了
Yes.
走吧  我的朋友
Come, my friends.
恩特(树人)要宣战了
The Ents are going to war.
我们可能
It is likely...
就此丧命
that we go to our doom.
这将是恩特(树人)
Last march...
最后的征途
of the Ents.
法拉米尔  奥克已经占领了东岸
Faramir! Orcs have taken the eastern shore.
它们的数量太多了
Their numbers are too great.
傍晚我们就要沦陷了
By nightfall we will be overrun.
弗罗多先生
Mr. Frodo?
它在召唤他  邪眼就快看到我了
It's calling to him, Sam. His Eye is almost on me.
坚持住  弗罗多先生 你不会有事
Hold on, Mr. Frodo. You'll be all right.
带他们去见我父亲
Take them to my father.
告诉他  法拉米尔献上大礼
Tell him Faramir sends a mighty gift.
一个可以扭转战局的强大武器
A weapon that will change our fortunes in this war.
你想知道波洛米尔到底怎么了吗
Do you want to know what happened to Boromir?
你想知道你哥哥为什么会死吗
You want to know why your brother died?
他发誓要保护弗罗多
He tried to take the Ring from Frodo
之后又想从他身上夺走魔戒
after swearing an oath to protect him!
他想杀了他
He tried to kill him!
是魔戒让你哥哥丧心病狂
The Ring drove your brother mad!
小心
Watch out!
弗罗多先生
Mr. Frodo?
它们来了
They're here.
They've come.
戒灵
Nazgûl!
待在这儿  不要被发现了
Stay here. Keep out of sight.
快隐蔽
Take cover!
要塞被攻陷
The fortress is taken.
都结束了
It is over.
你说只要有人守着  这要塞就绝不会攻陷
You said this fortress would never fall while your men defend it.
他们都还在死守  誓死奋战
They still defend it. They have died defending it.
它们要攻进来了
They're breaking in!
它们已经破门了
They're past the door!
没有其他路
Is there no other way
能让妇女和小孩逃出去吗
for the women and children to get out of the caves?
有没有其他路
Is there no other way?
有一条路
There is one passage.
通向山里
It leads into the mountains.
但他们逃不远  乌鲁克太多了
But they will not get far. The Uruk-hai are too many.
叫妇女和孩子进入通道  往山上逃
Tell the women and children to make for the mountain pass.
-堵住入口  -死了那么多人
- And barricade the entrance! - So much death.
人类要如何对抗这种仇恨
What can Men do against such reckless hate?
跟我一起冲出去
Ride out with me.
我们杀出去
Ride out and meet them.
为了荣耀战死沙场
For death and glory.
为了洛汗
For Rohan.
为了你的子民
For your people.
太阳出来了
The sun is rising.
待我五天后  迎着第一道曙光出现
Look to my coming at first light on the fifth day.
黎明之际
At dawn...
眺望东方
look to the east.
好
Yes.
锤手[洛汗第9代国王  锤手海尔姆]的号角
The horn of Helm Hammerhand...
将最后一次
shall sound in the Deep...
响彻海尔姆深谷
one last time.
好啊
Yes!
我们一同拔剑  并肩抗敌
Let this be the hour when we draw swords together.
杀戮  开始了
Fell deeds, awake.
以愤怒和毁灭的名义
Now for wrath...
让我们血染黎明
now for ruin and a red dawn.
冲啊  埃奥尔子嗣
Forth Eorlingas!
甘道夫
Gandalf.
希奥顿王孤军奋战
Theoden King stands alone.
他不是孤军奋战
Not alone.
洛汗骑士
Rohirrim!
伊奥梅尔
Eomer.
为国王而战
To the king!
好样的
Yes!
打得好  打得好
A hit. A fine hit.
把水库砸了
Break the dam!
放水
Release the river!
皮平  抓好了
Pippin! Hold on!
抓好了  小霍比特人
Hold on, little Hobbits.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
你要去哪儿
Where are you going?
是我
It's me.
你的山姆
It's your Sam.
你不认识山姆了吗
Don't you know your Sam?
我做不到  山姆
I can't do this, Sam.
我知道
I know.
这一切都错了
It's all wrong.
按理说  我们根本不该来这儿
By rights, we shouldn't even be here.
但是我们来了
But we are.
就像那陈年的故事  弗罗多先生
It's like in the great stories, Mr. Frodo.
那些英勇的传说
The ones that really mattered.
充满着黑暗和危险
Full of darkness and danger they were.
有时你根本不想知道故事的结局
And sometimes you didn't want to know the end...
因为怎么可能会有圆满结局
because how could the end be happy?
发生了那么多可怕的事
How could the world go back to the way it was...
世界怎么可能再回到当初
when so much bad had happened?
胜利
Victory!
我们胜利了
We have victory!
但是到最后  一切将会
But in the end, it's only a passing thing...
烟消云淡
this shadow.
黑暗也终将过去
Even darkness must pass.
崭新的一天终会到来
A new day will come.
当太阳再次升起  阳光将更加耀眼
And when the sun shines, it will shine out the clearer.
这些传说将一直伴随着你
Those were the stories that stayed with you...
令人难以忘怀
that meant something.
即时你太年轻  无法体会其中的深意
Even if you were too small to understand why.
我想我懂了  弗罗多先生
But I think, Mr. Frodo, I do understand.
我现在懂了
I know now.
传说中的这些家伙
Folk in those stories...
打过无数次退堂鼓  但是他们都没有退却
had lots of chances of turning back, only they didn't.
他们继续前进
They kept going...
因为他们心怀信念
because they were holding on to something.
我们有什么信念  山姆
What are we holding on to, Sam?
这个世上仍有美好存在  弗罗多先生
That there's some good in this world, Mr. Frodo.
值得我们为之奋战到底
And it's worth fighting for.
我想我们终于互相理解了
I think at last we understand one another,
弗罗多·巴金斯
Frodo Baggins.
你知道我国的律例  您父亲的律例
You know the laws of our country, the laws of your father.
要是放了他们  你难脱其咎
If you let them go, your life will be forfeit.
那就让我负责吧
Then it is forfeit.
放了他们
Release them.
不要靠近森林
Stay out of the forest!
Keep away from the trees!
总共干掉了
Final count...
-四十二个  -才四十二个
- 42. - 42?
对一个尖耳精灵来说  已经不错了
That's not bad for a pointy-eared Elvish princeling.
我正坐在第四十三个身上
I myself am sitting pretty on 43.
-四十三  -它已经死了
- 43. - He was already dead.
-它还在抽搐  -还在抽搐
- He was twitching. - He was twitching...
那是因为我的斧头扎着它的神经
because he's got my ax embedded in his nervous system!
他看上去心情不太好吧
He doesn't look too happy, does he?
一点都不好  梅里
Not too happy at all, Merry.
不过  我想从那上面看风景会很不错
Still, I suppose the view would be quite nice from up there.
是的  这塔盖得不赖
Oh, yes. It's a quality establishment.
听说佣人也不错
I hear the staff are very good.
-你在干什么  -没什么
- What are you doing? - Nothing.
-世界又恢复正常了  就这样  -还没呢
- The world's back to normal, that's all. - No, it isn't.
我饿死了
I'm starving.
碰碰运气  看看周围有没有什么好吃的
Good luck trying to find something decent around here.
估计只有死老鼠和发霉的面包
Probably dead rats and moldy bread.
萨茹曼的储藏室
Saruman's storeroom!
夏尔南区
简直难以置信
I don't believe it.
不可能
It can't be.
-就是这个  -长谷叶
- It is! - Longbottom Leaf.
夏尔南区最上等的烟叶
The finest pipe-weed in South Farthing.
太好了  一人一桶
It's perfect. One barrel each.
等等
Wait.
你说我们是不是该跟树须分享啊
Do you think we should share it with Treebeard?
分享
Share it?
算了吧
No. No.
都是死去的植物
Dead plant and all that.
他肯定接受不了
Don't think he'd understand.
可能是它的远房亲戚
Could be a distant relative.
我懂了
I get it.
不要着急
Don't be hasty.
太对了
Exactly.
这是条旧排水道
This is the old sewer.
位于河下方  直通城外
Runs right under the river through to the edge of the city.
尽头的森林可以掩护你们
You'll find cover in the woods there.
法拉米尔将军
Captain Faramir...
您彰显了自己的人格
you have shown your quality, sir.
非常高贵的人格
The very highest.
夏尔肯定是块宝地  甘姆吉先生
The Shire must truly be a great realm, Master Gamgee...
连园丁也这么伟大
where gardeners are held in high honor.
到森林了你们要怎么走
What road will you take once you reach the woods?
咕噜说有条路
Gollum says there's a path...
在米那斯魔古尔附近  可以通上山
near Minas Morgul that climbs up into the mountains.
奇立斯乌苟
Cirith Ungol?
-是这个名字吗  -不是
- Is that its name? - No.
不是
No!
-是的  -弗罗多
- Yes. - Frodo...
他们说米那斯魔古尔被黑暗笼罩
they say a dark terror dwells in the passes above Minas Morgul.
-你们不能走那条路  -只有这条路
- You cannot go that way. - It is the only way.
主人吩咐说我们必须去魔多
Master says we must go to Mordor,
所以必须试一试
so we must try.
我必须去
I must.
去吧  弗罗多  带着全人类的祝福上路
Go, Frodo. Go with the goodwill of all Men.
谢谢你
Thank you.
要是你敢害他们  你就死定了
May death find you quickly if you bring them to harm.
快点  跟上来
Come on, keep up.
弗罗多先生也不想让他们伤害你
Mr. Frodo didn't mean for them Rangers to hurt you.
你知道的吧
You know that, don't you?
他是想救你  懂吗
He was trying to save you, see?
救我
Save me?
所以别怪他
So there's no hard feelings.
过去的就过去吧
Forgive and forget.
不不不  不怪他
No, no, no hard feelings.
咕噜  咕噜
Gollum, Gollum.
是的  主人
Yes, master.
-好霍比特人  -你真通情达理
- Nice Hobbits. - Very decent of you.
非常通情达理  咕噜
Very decent, indeed, Gollum.
索隆的愤怒非同小可
Sauron's wrath will be terrible,
他很快就会报复我们
his retribution swift.
海尔姆深谷之役已经结束
The battle for Helm's Deep is over.
中洲世界的战争即将开始
The battle for Middle-earth is about to begin.
现在我们所有的希望
All our hopes now
都寄托在两个小霍比特人身上
lie with two little Hobbits...
他们在荒野中行进
somewhere in the wilderness.
你说  我们会不会被人传诵
I wonder if we'll ever be put into songs or tales.
什么
What?
人们会不会说
I wonder if people will ever say,
给我们讲讲弗罗多和魔戒的故事吧
"Let's hear about Frodo and the Ring."
他们会说  这是我最喜欢的故事
And they'll say, "Yes! That's one of my favorite stories."
爸爸  弗罗多真的很勇敢  对吧
"Frodo was really courageous, wasn't he, Dad?"
是的  孩子
"Yes, my boy".
他是最有名的霍比特人
The most famousest of Hobbits.
真的很了不起
And that's saying a lot."
你忘了还有个重要人物
Well, you've left out one of the chief characters:
勇敢的山姆怀斯N"Samwise the Brave."
我想多听听山姆的故事
I want to hear more about Sam.
没有山姆  弗罗多根本走不了这么远
Frodo wouldn't have got far without Sam.
弗罗多先生  别取笑我  我可是认真的
Now, Mr. Frodo, you shouldn't make fun. I was being serious.
我也是
So was I.
勇敢的山姆怀斯
"Samwise the Brave."
斯密戈
Smeagol?
我们可不会等你  快来
We're not going to wait for you. Come on.
主人
Master.
主人很照顾我们
Master looks after us.
主人不会伤害我们
Master wouldn't hurt us.
主人违背了他的誓言
Master broke his promise.
别问斯密戈
Don't ask Smeagol.
可怜的斯密戈
Poor, poor Smeagol.
主人背叛了我们
Master betrayed us.
邪恶  狡猾  虚伪
Wicked. Tricksy. False.
我们该把他卑鄙的脖子拧断
We ought to wring his filthy little neck.
杀了他  杀了他
Kill him! Kill him!
把他们两个都杀了
Kill them both!
然后我们就可以夺回宝贝
And then we take the precious...
我们就翻身做主人了
and we be the master!
那个胖霍比特人  他知道
But the fat Hobbit, he knows.
他总是盯着我们
Eyes always watching.
那我们就把他的眼睛挖出来
Then we stabs them out.
让他摸黑在地上打滚
Put out his eyeses and make him crawl.
好主意
Yes. Yes. Yes.
把他们俩都杀了
Kill them both.
好啊  不  不
Yes. No! No!
这太冒险  太冒险了
It's too risky. It's too risky.
他在哪里  去哪儿了
Where is he? Where has he gone?
-咕噜  你在哪儿  -斯密戈
- Hey, Gollum! Where are you? - Smeagol?
我们可以让她动手
We could let her do it.
没错  她做得到
Yes. She could do it.
是的  宝贝  她做得到
Yes, precious, she could.
等他们死了  我们就把宝贝抢过来
And then we takes it once they're dead.
一死就抢过来
Once they're dead.
快点  霍比特人  路还长着呢
Come on, Hobbits. Long ways to go yet.
斯密戈给你们带路
Smeagol will show you the way.
跟我来
Follow me...